<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The growth and spreading of hæresie. Set forth in a sermon preached before the Honorable House of Commons, on the 10th. day of March, being the day of their publike fast and humiliation for the growth of hæresie. / By Thomas Hodges, Minister of Gods Word, at Kensington. Published by order of the House of Commons.</title>
            <author>Hodges, Thomas, 1599 or 1600-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E379_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201396</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861913</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861913</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114059</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86433)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114059)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 60:E379[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The growth and spreading of hæresie. Set forth in a sermon preached before the Honorable House of Commons, on the 10th. day of March, being the day of their publike fast and humiliation for the growth of hæresie. / By Thomas Hodges, Minister of Gods Word, at Kensington. Published by order of the House of Commons.</title>
                  <author>Hodges, Thomas, 1599 or 1600-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. and E.M. for Abel Roper, at the signe of the Sun against Dunstans church in Fleetstreet.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Order to print on verso of title page. A variant has [10] pages of prelims with order to print on verso of leaf preceding title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 2nd II, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Heresy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114059:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114059:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GROWTH and SPREADING OF HAERESIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Set forth</hi> In a SERMON preached before the Honorable Houſe of COMMONS, on the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. day of <hi>March,</hi> being the day of their publike Faſt and Humiliation for the growth of Haereſie.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS HODGES, Miniſter of Gods Word, at <hi>KENSINGTON.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>Themiſt. orat. <hi>3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Melius aditum obſtruxiſſe, quàm aenam exegiſſe peccati.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Simpl. epiſt. 14. ad Zeno. imper.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Order of the Houſe of Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> and <hi>E. M.</hi> for <hi>Abel Roper,</hi> at the ſigne of the Sun againſt Dunſtans church in Fleetſtreet. 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:114059:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Jovis, <hi>11.</hi> Martii, <hi>1646.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, That Mr. <hi>Rows</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gewen</hi> do from this Houſe give thanks unto Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hodges</hi> for the great pains they took in their Sermons preached on the 10. of <hi>March</hi> 1646. at <hi>Margarets Weſtminſter,</hi> before the Houſe of Commons, being a day of publike Humiliation for the growth of Errors, Haereſies, &amp;c. And they are to deſire them to print their Sermons, wherein they are to have the like priviledge in printing of them, as others in the like kind uſually have had.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen. Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I appoint <hi>Abel Roper</hi> to print my Sermon.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>THO. HODGES.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114059:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Honourable HOUSE of COMMONS Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He GOD of heaven and earth, who is in himſelf an infinite ocean of Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction without either bank or bottom, hath been pleaſed by the overflowings of his power and goodneſſe to create this orderly glorious frame of Heaven and Earth out of nothing; the Earth he hath furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not only with great variety of excellent Beings, but alſo hath <note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 1.28. Pſal. 4.5, 6.</note> ſet over them a viſible Governour to be his Vicegerent, giving him dominion over all things beneath; Who although he be a little leſſe then the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, yet is he anſwerable for this truſt to God alone. This glorious God hath furniſhed him with <note n="(b)" place="margin">Job 38.11. 32 8.</note> Reaſon &amp; underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, more then the beaſts: &amp; that he might be more happy than the world can make him, he hath not only given him vaſt deſires, and ſuch a capacity as cannot be ſatisfied by Creature-fulneſſe, but hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned him to a higher end, a Heaven, which principally conſists in the <note n="(c)" place="margin">Rev. 22.4. 1 Cor. 13.12. Pſal. 16.11.</note> enjoyment of himſelf. But becauſe his reaſon is not <note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14.</note> ſufficient to diſcover this to him,
<pb facs="tcp:114059:3"/>
or bring him thither; therefore he hath ſent forth his <note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 43.3.</note> Light and Truth, the bleſſed <note n="(f)" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.3.</note> ſhinings of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to lead us to his dwelling, and to the place of his abode: which is not <note n="(g)" place="margin">Eph. 1.9.3, 9, &amp;c.</note> mans deſigne, but Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of his will and mind, pointing out the way to bliſſe. Yet hath he not appointed that man ſhould reach this end without oppoſition, and that not only from corruptions and <note n="(h)" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.11.</note> luſts within which fight againſt the ſoul, but alſo poor man is encountred by the <note n="(i)" place="margin">Eph. 6.12.</note> prince of darkneſſe, and ſpirituall wickedneſſes in high places: which makes his paſſage to his end ſo difficult, that did not that Almighty power that hath decreed him to the end, worke <note n="(k)" place="margin">1 Pet. 1 4, 5</note> effectually to the preſerving of him in the way, he muſt needs come ſhort of happineſſe. The truth is, amongſt all encounters he meets with, there is ſcarce any monſter that more endangers him then that Hydra <hi>Haereſie;</hi> which if it once gets place in the Head by aſſent, hath a generall influence upon his affections and actions, and is a fruitfull mother, producing quickly like ſome fertile weeds a numerous progeny. This enſuing diſcourſe will in ſome meaſure diſcover that unto you: Which you will not find polite, but very plain, in an unaffected dreſſe. But I beſeech you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, I did but bring up the Rear to my reverend Brother, in Application of that, which with great vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of Learning he doctrinally laid before you; and it was intended not to tickle the ears, or pleaſe the fancy of any, but to affect our hearts with a deep ſenſe of that ſad evil of Haereſie; to mourn for which, pray againſt it, and beg mercy for Church and State, we were aſſembled together. 'Twas your command that I ſhould publiſh it: In obedience to which, I have ſent it abroad under your protection, to be a remembrancer to
<pb facs="tcp:114059:3"/>
you, of your engagements to God, prayers, and reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons taken up that day, wherein for this cauſe you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted your ſoules before God, and ſupplicated the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">Cauſin. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> It is reported, That during the time the Olympi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an games laſted, there was not a Fly ſeen on Mount <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympus;</hi> the like is <note n="(m)" place="margin">Paul. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius praefat. ad Thargum.</note> affirmed of <hi>Onkelos</hi> his Chalde Paraphraſe. I cannot ſay much for the truth of either: But this I am ſure of, That it is not ſo with us; for the <note n="(n)" place="margin">
                  <p>Baal-zebub <hi>i. e.</hi> muſcarum princeps.</p>
                  <p>Shindleri pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taglot, vervo <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Prince of Flies,</hi> during your <hi>ſitting,</hi> hath raiſed ſuch ſwarms of flies an every corner of our Land, that many of our Congregations and Families are miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably Fly-blowne with Haereſies and corrupt Tenets. The truth is, the World is now grown old, neer its ruine, and 'tis no marvel if it dote &amp; be full of fancies. But when they are grown to ſuch a heigth of madneſſe, that they produce <hi>deſtructions,</hi> (as our Apoſtle ſtiles Haereſies in the Text) is it not time to cry to you for help? He was a Monſter of men, that could pleaſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with fidling, when <hi>Rome</hi> was on fire; or could make a ſport to ſee poor wretches ſwim for their lives and drown'd in <hi>Tiber,</hi> being thrown thither by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. We know you are Chriſtian Magiſtrates, who reſembling the God of heaven in his care for ſoules, will not endure that the Devil his enemy ſhould try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph here, or be worſhipped in his image <hi>Haereſie</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the inhabitants of this Iſland, ſeeing it is ſo oppoſite to the firſt Truth, and dangerous to peoples im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall ſpirits.</p>
            <p>If it ſhall be thought, that I have not ſufficiently pointed out what I mean by <hi>Haereſie;</hi> I anſwer, My reverend Brother did prevent me; and as I did not in Preaching, ſo I will not in Printing, <hi>actum agere,</hi> but
<pb facs="tcp:114059:4"/>
referre my ſelf to his deſcription of it. Only give me leave to ſay, That if the Opinion overthrows any Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Truth, I intend that, by the name <hi>Haereſie:</hi> if it ſhake or looſen the foundation-stones, it is not to be paſt by; Little ſerpents grow great ones by degrees, if they be let alone; the Egge may quickly become a Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atrice, nay a Flying-ſerpent. But as for more petty differences in opinion, concerning things not much material, either not determined in Gods word at all, or after ſuch a manner as is dubious, not only to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, but alſo to many Churches of Christ, as ſome particulars perhaps in Diſcipline, and the like; ſo the peace of Church and State may ſtand with it; if the perſons profeſſing it be of an humble &amp; conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit to Authority, not stubborn or refractory, but willing to open their eyes to further light, not plotting nor contriving the overthrow of others, nor ſeeking to undermine what tends to order &amp; ſafety, nor have their mouths open to cenſure, condemne, and raile againſt others; Such perſons I have <note n="(o)" place="margin">Multa do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanda ingeniis puto, ſed do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanda vitia, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> portenta ſunt. <hi>Senec. praefat. l. 1. contr.</hi>
               </note> not the leaſt aim at in any part of this enſuing diſcourſe, only wiſh them the ſpirit of judgement and of a ſounder mind. But as for foul-mouth'd Haereſie, I wiſh the ſame <note n="(p)" place="margin">Joh. 2.15, 16, 17.</note> zeale that was in Chriſt, may act ſtrongly in you, to <hi>whip them out of the Temple.</hi> God hath dealt by you, as <note n="(q)" place="margin">Eph. 6.11.</note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſhuerus</hi> by <hi>Mordecai,</hi> cloathed you with his own robe and title, called you <note n="(r)" place="margin">Pſal. 82 1, 6.</note> Gods, and put <note n="(s)" place="margin">Rom. 13.1, &amp;c.</note> power into your hand: I hope it ſhall ever be your Motto with the bleſsed Apoſtle, <note n="(t)" place="margin">2 Cor. 13.8</note> 
               <hi>We can do nothing againſt, but for the Truth.</hi> If for the Truth, then certainly againſt Error, Truths chief oppoſite. I look at you as <note n="(u)" place="margin">Cant. 3.7, 8.</note> the ſpirituall <hi>Solomons</hi> guard of valiant men about his bed: <hi>Error</hi> is got into Chriſts bed-chamber,
<pb facs="tcp:114059:4"/>
mens ſoules, and there attempts to aſſault Him that is the Truth, in the hearts of his people. We are confident you are too well-affected to this King of Kings, to ſuffer it: Yet give me leave to tell you, That many of theſe unworthy people have not a little boaſted of encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from Above, as they call it; but we believe it not, knowing that their tongues are much their own, and that they are great maſters of untruths: We rather think it is here, as it was in the ſpeech of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>VI.</hi> who when a man that counterfeited a recovering his ſight at his dead <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkle the D. of <hi>Gloceſters</hi> tombe, was brought unto him, the man hoping by magnifying the holineſſe and vertue of his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkle to have gained ſome reward from him; He having found out by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry that he was a man of a wicked life, in ſtead of giving credit to him, told him, That he knew his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkles goodneſſe ſo well, that he was ſure, if he had ſeen, he would rather have pluckt out both his eyes, then have reſtored either of them to him. The like we may ſay of you. Yet give me leave in all humility to repreſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you no ſmall affliction to good men, which is, The fruitfulneſſe of the <hi>Preſſe</hi> in producing monſtrous miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhapen births: 'Tis believed by wiſe men, <note n="(x)" place="margin">Sueton. vit. Tiberii.</note> that <hi>Tiberias</hi> as much was <note n="(z)" place="margin">Non ſunt commiſeratione digni, qui tanti putant caput potius quàm dictum perdere. <hi>Sen. l. 2. contr.</hi>
               </note> miſtaken in that connivence of his at ſuch kind of traſh as this, which might tend like a ſpark to ſome terrible flame, as almoſt in any act of his government.</p>
            <p>To conclude; I beſeech you do not delay this buſines, There is nothing more excellent then Gods truth, nor more of concernment then Mans ſoule; both lie a bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. It is obſerved that the <hi>Spartans,</hi> too much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the weakneſſe and puſillanimity of the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans,</hi> made but petty inroads upon them by ſmall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:
<pb facs="tcp:114059:5"/>
had they put forth the utmoſt of their power, the <hi>Thebans</hi> were a people at that time ſo ſluggiſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apt to reſiſt, they might eaſily have ſubdued them; but by theſe ſmall parties they ſo awakened them, that they made them warriours, and after a grievous ſlaughter found their own error and miſtake too late.</p>
            <p>The GOD of heaven direct and guide your Counſels. Which is, and ſhall ever be the Prayer of him that is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt humble and affectionate ſervant</hi> in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>THO: HODGES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114059:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS at <hi>Margarets Weſtminſter,</hi> on the tenth of <hi>March</hi> 1646. being a day of publique Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation for the growth of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Haereſies, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 PETER 2.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And many ſhall follow their pernitious wayes, by reaſon of whom the way of truth ſhall be evill ſpoken of.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Learned and Reverend Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath ſet before you the <note n="(a)" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.8</note> 
               <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude and pervert ſoules. It is my taske, to ſhew you the havock they make of Gods inheritance. Hee hath diſcourſed of the <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doraes</hi> box, and I ſhall ſhew you the miſchiefe that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114059:6"/>
comes by the opening thereof. You have ſeen by this diſcourſe the black face of damnable error; and one would think that ſuch ſtuffe ſhould ſcarce bee own'd in the world: Yet here in the words of my Text behold the peoples madneſſe, <hi>many ſhall follow their pernitious wayes, &amp;c.</hi> In which words ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The <hi>thriving</hi> and <hi>growth</hi> of Hereſy; <hi>many ſhall follow their pernicious wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The <hi>ſad ſequel</hi> or <hi>fruit</hi> of this; <hi>by reaſon of whom the way of truth ſhall be evill ſpoken of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, In the <hi>growth</hi> of theſe damnable errors, obſerve,
<list>
                  <item>1 Their Nature and Character, ſtiled here in the Text <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Deſtructions.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 Their attraction or rather infection and faſcination; And in that take notice of,
<list>
                        <item>1 Their efficacy, they ſhall ſo prevaile, and overcome the wills of ſome, that they <hi>ſhall follow their pernicious wayes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 Their ſpreading; Not a few, but <hi>Many</hi> ſhall be perverted by them.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in the ſad ſequel of this perverſion, obſerve
<list>
                  <item>1 An Epithite given by the Apoſtle to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, <hi>Tis the way of truth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 The foule carriage of many wicked men towards it, or the courſe uſage it finds at the hands of ſome in the world, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>i. e. It ſhall be blaſphemed or evil ſpoken of.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 The reaſon, or root of this, <hi>By reaſon of whom,</hi> i. e. of thoſe that are by theſe damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble errors ſeduced and led aſtray by theſe falſe teachers.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:114059:6"/>But firſt I ſhall ſpeak of the firſt part, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerve,</hi> 1. The <hi>Character</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> of Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call courſes, rightly here in this Text ſtiled by our Apoſtle <hi>Deſtructions.</hi> Hence compared to a life-deſtroying, ſenſe-devouring <note n="(b)" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>Gangrene,</hi> to a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.19.</note> ſhipwrack, to a horrible <note n="(d)" place="margin">Rev. 12.15.</note> flood, by which <note n="(e)" place="margin">Med. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocal. in cap <hi>12</hi> &amp; vers. <hi>15.</hi> cum al is.</note> ſome learned expoſitors underſtand eſpecially the <hi>Arrian</hi> hereſy, not excluding others alſo. O who is able to reckon up the ruins they bring, the ſad deſtructions they produce to <hi>Societies</hi> or <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, look into the Church, there is no man that is moderately ver'ſt in Church-ſtory, but muſt needs take notice, that theſe damnable errors have been almoſt in every Century notoriouſly deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive there; robbing, and diſpoyling her of not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly her <note n="(f)" place="margin">Cant. 2.15</note> tender grapes, but many choice orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, learned inſtruments, who might have been more uſeful to her, alienating them from her, nay many times ingaging them as ſoreſt oppoſites againſt her peace and verity: Witneſſe of old <note n="(g)" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>Demas,</hi> 
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> 
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">2 Tim. 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>Phygellus</hi> and <hi>Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes, Nicholas, Ebion</hi> and <hi>Cerinthus, Menander, Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus,</hi> with many others. And in later time <hi>Muncer, Swenkfeild, Servetus, David George, Socinus,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others.</p>
            <p>What horrid exacerbations of mind have they raiſed, which have grown to provoking language, and have not reſted there, but proceeded to blowes, yea blood; witneſſe that hot conteſt at <hi>Alexandria</hi> between the <hi>Arrians</hi> and the Orthodox; where (to uſe <note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. in vita Conſtant. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> his words) they fought together, and kil'd each other like ſwarmes of gnats in the ayre.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114059:7"/>
How have they defiled her purity with lothſome pollutions in Doctrine and manners? witneſſe thoſe filthy dreamers in St. <note n="(l)" place="margin">Iude 8.</note> 
               <hi>Judes</hi> time <hi>who defiled the fleſh, deſpiſed dominion, and ſpeak evill of dignities.</hi> Thoſe abominable beaſtly men, whom no leſſe title then <note n="(m)" place="margin">Some cald them <hi>Bort ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> from their beaſtly life.</note> 
               <hi>Gnoſtici</hi> would content, as if they had been the only inhabitants of <hi>Goſhen,</hi> and all the world beſide had been benighted in Egyptian darkneſſe. And I beſeech you, how much in later times have our <hi>Germane Anabaptiſts, or Engliſh Libertines</hi> in their aſſertions, or lives faln ſhort of their monſtrous predeceſſors? How have they like fumes out of the bottomleſſe pit clouded her verity? In the Church of <note n="(n)" place="margin">Gal. 3.1. and 5.7. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Galatia,</hi> was not the ſoule-ſaving Doctrine of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification almoſt totally eclipſed? and in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> 
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> the article of the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhrewdly ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by theſe? did not the wretched doctrine of <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Nicholaitans</hi> paſſe with many for currant in <note n="p" place="margin">Rev. 2.14.20.</note> 
               <hi>Pergamus?</hi> And was not the bright ſhining of truth offuſcated by thoſe in <hi>Thyatirus?</hi> How did truth ſeem to have forſaken the Church in the dayes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> when the world (to uſe <hi>Jeroms</hi> expreſſion) groaned to ſee it ſelfe become an <hi>Arrian,</hi> when a whole <note n="(q)" place="margin">Socrates. ſch. Eccleſ. hiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> Synod of <hi>Arrians</hi> at <hi>Tyre</hi> condemn poor <hi>Athanaſius</hi> for maintaining the eternall Diety of Chriſt? How have theſe damnable errors when once they have got footing in the ſpirits of men turn'd them into beaſts of prey, <hi>cruell</hi> 
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">Phil 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>dogs, rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous</hi> 
               <note n="(s)" place="margin">Act. 20 29.</note> 
               <hi>wolves, devouring lyons;</hi> not reſting ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied where their power could reach and prevaile, without the inflicting of the ſaddeſt cruelties, and foreſt deſtructions they could invent, upon the moſt Orthodox profeſſors of truth? We need to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114059:7"/>
ſeek for proof of this no further than the <note n="(t)" place="margin">Socrat. hiſt. Eccleſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi> Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſ. Apolog. Victor. de perſecut. Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Arrian</hi> haereſy; how cruell and bloody were they to the ſervants of Chriſt; exciting the Magiſtrate to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turpate them, loading them with ſlanders, baniſhing them from their Countries, ſcourging, and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, cutting out their tongues, nay not ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied without their precious lives. Thus we ſee that whether wee look at theſe damnable errors in their own nature, or in their ſubject in whom they reſide, they are truly by the Apoſtle in the Text ſtiled <hi>Deſtructions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, but fares the Common-wealth any bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter where theſe take place? Have not theſe damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble errors deſtroyed its peace by tumultuous inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, and horrid outrages? what a terrible tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt was raiſed by <note n="(x)" place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>50.</hi> ad Bonif. &amp; Epiſt. <hi>68.</hi> ad Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuar. &amp; lib. 3. cont. creſcon.</note> 
               <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and <hi>Circumcelliones,</hi> men of the ſame humor with them, and what out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages were committed by them; who pretended to more piety than others, but expreſt the contrary, by their rapines, robberies, and miſcheivous courſes? Nor could they bee taken off, till <hi>Honorius</hi> the <note n="(y)" place="margin">Paul. diac. lib. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> Emperor was fain to ſend <hi>Dulcius</hi> with an army to ſuppreſſe them. How have theſe errors many times ſubverted the very foundations of States, while ſome of them in their own nature have been ſo directly oppoſite to the being, or binding of Lawes, to the authority of Magiſtrates (as the <hi>Moniches</hi> of old, the <hi>Munster</hi> faction of late) that where they have taken place, the ligaments of States have been (ſo far as theſe have prevailed) ſo miſerably broken, and left in ſo ſad a confuſion under a pretence of <note n="(z)" place="margin">Quidam ut imperium ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertant, liberta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſi ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terint ipſam ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredientur. <hi>Corn. Tacit.</hi>
               </note> liberty, that had not their extirpation been the more ſpeedy they had certainly buried thoſe people where they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114059:8"/>
reigned in utter confuſion and deſolation. Not only making them acceſſory to their own deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whilſt with their own hands they ſhould effect their ruine; but alſo ingaging him who is the God of order and truth to become their enemy, and pour out the teſtimonies of his vengeance from heaven upon them: Somtimes by a more immediate hand, as <note n="(x)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Paul. Diac.</hi> lib. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Antioch,</hi> a nurcery of hereſies was firſt ſore ſhaken, and after with fire from heaven conſumed; <hi>Nichomedia</hi> a place where the <hi>Arrians</hi> were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to meet, ſwallowed up of an earth-quake. And frequently by the mediate hand of men, who are his ax, rod, and ſtaffe of his indignation; whoſe ſpirits hee ſtirs up to take vengeance on his behalfe; ſuch in former times were <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, who ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht <hi>Arrius;</hi> 
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Socr. ſchol. hiſt. eccl.</hi> l. 5. c. 10. <hi>Evagr. hiſt. eccl.</hi> l. 4. c. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Theodoſius</hi> expeld all hereticks that were againſt the faith of one ſubſtance; <hi>Juſtinian</hi> publiſhed ſharp edicts, and ſorely puniſhed hereticks, with divers others. And in later times <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth againſt the Weſtphalian crue; alſo the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of <hi>Geneva</hi> burning <hi>Servetus</hi> for his Antitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarian hereſie, with many other examples of this. Thus you have ſeen, how deſtructive theſe damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hereſies are in ſocieties.</p>
            <p>Secondly, but are they leſſe pernitious to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons, whether ringleaders, or ſuch as are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by them? Certainly no; but I may truly take up the words of the Prophet <note n="(a)" place="margin">Eſay. 59.5.</note>, <hi>They hatch Cockatrice egges, and weave the ſpiders web: hee that eateth of their egges dieth, and that which is cruſhed, breaketh forth into a viper.</hi> In which place <note n="(b)" place="margin">Hieron. in Epiſt. ad Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pri.</note> 
               <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> thinks the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> doth lively ſet forth the nature of hereſies, and the work of hereticks.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114059:8"/>
How is it often the deſtruction of their bodies, whilſt their erroneous mind puts them upon the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting or practiſing that which either by too much exceſſe and riotous courſes ruines nature, as the <note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.10, 12, 13, &amp;c.</note> Libertines of former and later time; Or elſe on the contrary, by too much <note n="(c)" place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.21, 22.</note> auſterity and ſelf-elected rigidity, ſink in time the Body, and bring it to the duſt of death?</p>
            <p>But if none of theſe take place, how often is the God of heaven ſo far provoked, eſpecially againſt the founders, or principall abetters and maintainers of them; that vengeance marks them with ſome eminent and notorious badge of Gods diſpleaſure, by ſome ſad and diſmal ruine? <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Theodoret eccleſ. hist.</hi> l. 3. c. 14.</note> When <hi>Arrius</hi> was in the midſt of his pomp and pride, the hand of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven allots him a death-bed, and death loathſome like his Opinion. <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Evagr. hiſt. eccl.</hi> l. 1. c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Neſtorius</hi> his tongue was eaten with worms; <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> a great defender of the Eutychi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an hereſie, was ſmitten with a thunder-bolt; <note n="(f)" place="margin">Palmeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eteron.</note> 
               <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympius</hi> who publickly deteſted the Trinity, was ſtruck with three lightnings whereby his body was burnt.</p>
            <p>Yet however their bodyes ſpeed, moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are alwayes deſtructive to their better part the ſoul; <note n="(g)" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.6.</note> benighting their minds, turning their light into darkeneſſe, and leaving them to innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by wayes of <note n="(h)" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.8.</note> ruine and deſtruction. Many times ſpoyling their <note n="(i)" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.10, 11, 12. 2 Tim. 4.2.</note> Conſciences of peace, by overthrowing the very grounds and roots thereof, as Chriſts ſatisfaction; the comfortable doctrine of Juſtification, by the Papiſts and Socinians; which being taken away, what is left to a poore diſtreſſed ſoule afflicted with the ſight and ſence of ſinne,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114059:9"/>
a knife or halter, the too too ordinary refuges of dark diſtracted minds?</p>
            <p>But however an Erring mind may enjoy a ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing peace, (which for the moſt part is rather to be ſtiled ſottiſh ſtupidity, or carnal ſecurity, then Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian tranquillity) Yet alwayes, anſwerable to the degree of falſhood in the haereſie aſſerted, there is a pollution and ſtain thereby derived to the perſon maintaining <note n="(c)" place="margin">Lev. 13.29, 30, 42, 43, 44.</note> it. Leproſie in the head as truly made a Leper, as on any other part; neither doth it reſt in the head, but as defluxions from the brain overthrow the ſtomach, ſo haereſies corrupt the other faculties of the ſoul, and frequently diſcover themſelves in the filthy ungodly practiſes of thoſe that entertain them; Some haereſies directly mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating againſt all piety in life and converſation; as that of the Libertines of old, who conceived that the diſtinction of Works into good and bad, was but an invention of men; and that no works were really bad in their own nature, but were to be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned evil only ſo far forth as he that wrought them thought them ſo to be. And in our dayes, the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine aſſertions that ſo much prevaile upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable ſpirits; as, That there is no reſurrection of the fleſh; That the works which are wrought by the body ſhall never be accounted for; That God is the author of evill works, as well as of good; That men are freed that believe, from obedience to the Moral Law and the like.</p>
            <p>Thus haereſies <note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.5.</note> corrupt mens minds, deſtroy good Conſcience, pollute their Lives, rob them of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, peace, piety, indeed all reall ſpirituall worth. As rottenneſſe in an apple, or a flaw or cloud in a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114059:9"/>
ſtone, ſo far as theſe prevail, all real value ceaſes; ſo we may juſtly aſſert, that look how far haereſie prevails, ſo far forth the ſpirit of ſuch a one is little, yea nothing worth; <note n="(o)" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.20.</note> making them <hi>veſſels of wood, ſtone, diſhonour:</hi> 
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">Cypr. l. <hi>3.</hi> ep. <hi>3.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> ep. <hi>2.</hi> Aug. l. <hi>3.</hi> de bap. cont. Donatiſt. c. <hi>18, 19,</hi> &amp;c.</note> (ſo <hi>Cyprian, Auſtin,</hi> and divers others underſtand that place in <hi>Timothy</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch kinde of perſons as theſe.) But that which is worſt of all, the height of miſery, and dregs of vengeance; <note n="(q)" place="margin">Gal. 5.20, 21.</note> The nature, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary conſequent of Haereſie unrepented of, is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive the ſoul of happineſſe. And moſt certainly, though it may bring a man into an imaginary ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual heaven, like that of <hi>Demaes</hi> here; yet will it bring them, if obſtinately perſiſted in, into a <note n="(r)" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.10, 11.</note> hell here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. And however they may blaze and ſhine in the opinion of their own Faction, or others here; St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells you, like ſhooting gliding meteors, there is an eternal <note n="(s)" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.17 Jude 13.</note> night of darkneſſe abides them in the other world for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> See then (I beſeech you) worthy Senators, in   what rank to reckon them that patronize, plead for, or ſeek a Toleration of Haereſies of you; or that would tie your hands from executing judgement upon Hereticall ſeducers of the people; or from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the growth, or extirpating of ſo banefull and pernicious a weed as Haereſie is. What, would they ingage you in the guilt of ſoules? or the ruine of Church and State, which you ſeek to preſerve? The Lord rebuke thee Satan, who hath pulled theſe men as a brand out of the fire. Look therefore, I beſeech you, upon ſuch, as men, That care not for your reputation, though you leave your names for a curſe and by-word to poſterity; Regard not your
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114059:10"/>
ſecurity; Have no bowels of pity to poor ſoules; Are void of Publikeneſſe of ſpirit; Not regarding to ſee <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in proſperity, nor peace upon <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But as an Antidote againſt their oratory, I beſeech you conſider, the greatneſſe of your truſt for the Peoples ſafety; the ſtrictneſſe of your Covenant-engagement; the frequencie of your Declarations and Remonſtrances againſt them; your Replies to reproaches that have been caſt upon you, as if you favoured them; And laſtly, I beſeech you conſider the ruining and deſtroying nature of Hereſie, to Church, Commonwealth, Souls, Bodies. <note n="(t)" place="margin">Cant. 2.14.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>take us the Foxes, the little Foxes that ſpoile the Vines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> I beſeech you take notice, 'Tis no ſmall judgment for a people to be <note n="(u)" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.10, 11.</note> given up to believe a lye; to be ſo far deſerted by God, as that Hereſies ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile over them: <note n="(w)" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.26.</note> 'Tis as the Devil would have it, <note n="(x)" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.10.11.</note> A trophie of his victory, a ſigne of Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a Prognoſtick of Ruine, <note n="(y)" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.17.</note> a deadly diſeaſe, a mark of <note n="(z)" place="margin">Rev. 13.8.</note> Reprobation; a terrible ſhipwrack, a certain ingulf of them in the <note n="(a)" place="margin">Rev. 14.9, 10.</note> participation of the ſaddeſt plagues and vengeance. O how can we weep enough this day for the daughter of our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; The Lords people are led captive; the Church is ecclipſed, and looks like a <note n="(b)" place="margin">Jer. 12.9.</note> ſpeckled bird a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the nations; The Commonwealth rotters; Soules are defiled; And hell is, I feare, too much filled with theſe Erring creatures.</p>
            <p>We Miniſters have need to weep, for want of courage, watchfulneſſe, zeal. Chriſt may complain of us as <note n="(c)" place="margin">Euſeb. eccl. hiſt. l. <hi>3</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>John</hi> did of that Biſhop, <hi>I have made a ſweet keeper of my brothers ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:114059:10"/>You Magiſtrates had need to weep for want of <note n="(d)" place="margin">Vt laudan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da patientia, ſic timendum ne culpetur in ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium toleran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis negligentia. <hi>Aug. ſerm. 14. de verb. Apoſt.</hi>
               </note> Warmth, Heedfulneſſe, Expedition, and for your cruel mercy towards Seducers. Are not you ſtiled <note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 47.9.</note> Sheilds, <note n="(f)" place="margin">Nch. 9.27</note> Saviours, <note n="(g)" place="margin">Iſa. 44.18.</note> Shepherds, <note n="(h)" place="margin">Iſa. 49 23.</note> Nurſing Fathers to Church and State? And God forbid you ſhould be <note n="(i)" place="margin">Pſal. 115.6.</note> like <hi>Davids</hi> Idol, have eyes, and not take notice of theſe; eares, and not heare the ſad cryes of a diſtracted afflicted peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple againſt them; hands, and ſhould not ſmite and cut off ſuch wicked workers <note n="(k)" place="margin">Pſal. 101.8.</note> from the city of our God. Parents and Maſters had need to weep, for their heedleſneſſe, and perfunctorineſſe; that they have no more watcht over their tender ſpring, nor made it their buſines to <note n="(l)" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.4, 9.</note> ground them in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of religion, for want of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they have eaſily been <note n="(m)" place="margin">Eph. 5.14.</note> ſeduced &amp; cheated by theſe hereticall Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors who lie in wait to deceive. And have they not abundantly obtained their purpoſe? Did ever the former ages produce more hideous Monſters than wee have riſen up amongſt us in this poor I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land? Are there not many <hi>Arrians,</hi> who hold that damnable error againſt the eternall Deity of Jeſus Chriſt? Some <hi>Valentinians,</hi> who oppoſe the reality of his taking fleſh of the Virgin Mary? <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionites,</hi> who deny the verity of his ſufferings? <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks,</hi> who pretend to new lights and revelations, but are too much like them in the wildneſſe of their Opinions, and profaneneſſe of their Lives? And very many, of whom wee may ſay as <note n="(n)" place="margin">Multifer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me monſtrum. Epiphan.</note> 
               <hi>Epiphanius</hi> of <hi>Ebion,</hi> that hee was a Monſter of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhapes, holding all errors together; The <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi> abomination, the Jewes name, the <hi>Nazare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> opinion, the <hi>Cerinthians</hi> forme, the <hi>Corpocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:114059:11"/>
improbity, and the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> profeſſion, and is not here cauſe to weep?</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">Luk. 19.41</note> Chriſt wept over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> out of a contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of thoſe ſad confuſions and ruines that were at hand; and have not we juſt cauſe to mourn for our ſelves and for our children, when we may juſtly in a very true ſenſe take up the <note n="(n)" place="margin">Pſal. 80.13, 14.</note> Pſalmiſts ſad complaint: <hi>Thou haſt broken down their hedges, ſo that they that paſſe by devoure it; the Bore out of the wood doth waſte it, and the wild beaſt of the field doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure it.</hi> Is not here cauſe to weep?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> See, 'tis no ſmall mercy to be preſerved from Haereſie in erring times, and to ſtand on the vantage ground of Truth, from thence taking view of the dangerous encounters, fierce charges, boiſterous blaſts and billows which indanger the utter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and ingulfing of poor ſouls in everlaſting ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, whileſt we our ſelves dwell in the ſerene aire and ſafe fort of Truth, freed from that giddineſſe and deſtruction which lights on others. But let me tell you, We muſt take heed that this view we take be with abnegation and humility: <hi>Not to us O Lord, not to us;</hi> or with the <note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Cor. 15.10.</hi> Non est devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis dediſſe prope totum, ſed fraudis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuiſſe mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum. <hi>Proſp.</hi>
               </note> Apoſtle, <hi>Not I but the grace of God that was with me.</hi> With praiſe and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, for this mercy to our ſelves; with prayer and ſupplication for poore ſoules, that either are in danger to be inſnared by them, or are already captivated, that they may eſcape out of this ſnare of the devil; With pity and commiſeration towards them, taking notice that we our ſelves are but men, and may be <note n="(p)" place="margin">Quid de me talis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio feciſſet, &amp;c. <hi>Aug. Gal. 6 1.</hi>
               </note> tempted; With help &amp; adjuvation, <note n="(q)" place="margin">Jude 22, 23</note> yet <hi>putting a difference, ſome pulling with feare, as it were out of the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> 
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114059:11"/>Exhortation to People. You ſee there is no dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying   with Haereſies, for they are Deſtructions: Therefore <note n="(r)" place="margin">1 Joh. 4.1.</note> try before you truſt, <hi>whether the ſpirits be of God or no.</hi> Thus did the religious <note n="(s)" place="margin">Act. 17.11.</note> 
               <hi>Bereans,</hi> they ſearched the Scriptures, whether the things St. Paul preached were ſo or no. Poiſon is not a thing to be dallied with, ſeeing it deſtroyes nature, and cauſes death: what's matter though it be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in a golden cup? Beware, I beſeech you, of that fool-hardineſſe which is found in too many in our dayes, who venture to complement with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious errors and erroneous perſons, reſolving ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to keep their minds free from engagement to them; or if they go ſo far as to ſip, and out of curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity take a taſte of them, yet they determine to maintain in themſelves a mind free to fall off at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. But <note n="(t)" place="margin">Sed enim febrem ut ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum &amp; de cauſa &amp; de potentia ſua, ut notum eſt, abominamus potius quàm miramur, &amp; quantum in nobis eſt prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavemus, non habentes aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem ejus in noſtra poteſtate. Haereſes verò mortem aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam &amp; majoris ignis ardorem inferentes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt quidam mirari quòd poſſint hoc, quàm devitare nè poſſint, &amp;c. <hi>Tertul. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. haeret.</hi>
               </note> I beſeech you conſider, they are of too <note n="(u)" place="margin">Rev. 17.4.</note> intoxicating a nature, filling the ſoule with a ſpiritual <hi>vertigo,</hi> deſtroying by degrees the light of the mind, <note n="(w)" place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> faſcinating and bewitching the ſpirits of thoſe that ſwallow them. Neither is it a thing unuſuall, but common with God in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, to <note n="(x)" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2, 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>deliver up ſuch to ſtrong deluſion that believe a lye, that receive not the truth in the love thereof.</hi> Oh then, how is it poſſible they ſhould ever ſcape, <note n="(y)" place="margin">Libera vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas ſine gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, tota viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſa cupiditae eſt, <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> when grace is with-held, whereby they ſhould eſcape out of theſe ſnares of the devil, and they left to his depths and wiles, under the conduct of an erring mind. If therefore thou throweſt thy ſelf off from the pinacle of the temple, never think thou canſt ſtop where thou pleaſeſt: But as Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cautions his drunkard againſt that vice, <note n="(z)" place="margin">Prov. 23, 31.</note> 
               <hi>Look not upon the wine when it is red; when it giveth his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114059:12"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114059:12"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:114059:13"/>
colour in the glaſſe, when it moveth it ſelf aright.</hi> So ſay I to thee, take heed of being flattered into a liking of untruths, either from the glorious colours and pretences of more ſanctity, New light, clearer diſcoveries of Truth, Chriſtian liberty, or the like: for if Haereſies had not ſome plauſible varniſh to ſet them off, they would be contemned and deteſted by all, being in themſelves of horrid hue, of an ugly viſage and hag-like countenance; but it is their paint that makes them paſſable. <note n="(a)" place="margin">Haereſes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natu, non viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curibus pulchrae ſunt; foris ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecus ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> nomine juſtitiae ſe dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ant, &amp;c <hi>Aug. ſerm. 50. in Job.</hi>
               </note> Their cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is fair, but their inward frame is monſtrous; they outwardly ſhine with the gilt of truth and righteouſneſſe, but inwardly there is nothing but darkneſſe and impiety in them, being conceived in the womb of <note n="(b)" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.3, 4.</note> a dark elated mind, cheriſhed by vain imaginations, ſelf-eſtimation and ends; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, moſt frequently, to <note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Pet. 2, 3.</note> gain reputation and the like advantages; but alwayes terminating (if perſiſted in) in ſad <note n="(d)" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.10, 11, 12. 2 Pet. 2.3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ruines and deſtructions. Yet ſee the madneſſe of the people; Not a <hi>few,</hi> but <hi>many,</hi> ſayes our Apoſtle, <hi>ſhall follow their pernicious wayes.</hi> Which is the ſecond thing in my Text.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Part </seg>2</label> 2. The attraction, or rather infection and faſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of theſe pernicious Errors: they are ſo effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious, that they overcome; and ſo ſpreading, that not a few, but <hi>many</hi> are conquered and led captive by them. This <hi>[ſhall]</hi> in my Text, is far from a precept; for it is prohibited to follow the falſe <note n="(e)" place="margin">Deut. 13.1, 2, 3, &amp;c.</note> Prophet of old, or the falſe <note n="(f)" place="margin">Jude 19.20, 21, &amp;c. Epheſ. 4.14.</note> Apoſtles and erring Teachers in the New Teſtament. Nor is there in it the leaſt ſhew of a Toleration from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which God abhors, threatning ſad judgments and breathing flames againſt the <note n="(g)" place="margin">Rev. 2.15.</note> Church of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114059:13"/>
               <hi>Pergamus,</hi> for the <hi>Nicolaitans;</hi> and againſt the Church of <hi>Thiatyra,</hi> for ſuffering <hi>Jeſabel</hi> to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce his ſervants. But 'tis an infallible Prediction: for God was (as it were) the active underſtanding to this bleſſed Apoſtle, by whoſe revelation he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw this ſad prevailing Apoſtaſie deſtroying not a <hi>few,</hi> but <hi>many.</hi> 
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">Baron. Annal.</note> This Epiſtle was written about the year of Chriſt 65. not long before his death, as himſelfe hints in his firſt chap. of this Epiſt. and 14. verſ. <hi>Knowing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that ſhortly I muſt put off this earthly tabernacle, even as our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath ſhewed me.</hi> Which fell out about the year 67. And how ſoon after, according to this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical prediction, did ariſe <hi>Cerinthus, Baſilides, Carpocrates, Saturninus, Marcion, Valentinus</hi> who drew no ſmall numbers, but multitudes in thoſe Eaſtern parts became followers of their blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos monſtrous Tenets. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of about 400 years, wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of the riſe of almoſt fourſcore ſects and ſorts of Haereticks; ſome more, ſome leſſe differing from each other, but all of them enemies to the truth. By theſe, alas, how ſoon was the Lords field, his Church ouer run with tares and weeds? How ſwiftly did Haereſie run from Eaſt to Weſt, like fire in ſtubble?</p>
            <p>But this <hi>[Many ſhall follow]</hi> in my Text, is not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fined within the narrow compas of ſome few Centuries of years after the Apoſtles death, but is extenſive to the end of the world, as may appear by a due conſideration of the laſt chap. of this 2. epiſtle. 'Tis true, the <hi>Eaſt</hi> firſt bred haereſies, as having the riper and more nimble wits, the Devil alſo bending his power betimes to make them adulterate Truth,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114059:14"/>
and ſtrangle it in its infancie: And oh happy had it been for thouſands of ſouls, if Haereſies birth and funeral had been at the ſame place &amp; time together: but the old Serpent uſed all his skill to make it long-lived; endeavouring by his huckſters to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey it from place to place; that thus it living in many ſoiles, and ſoules, there might be the leſſe danger of its utter extirpation. He quickly found choice Agents for his purpoſe: Some out of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, as <note n="(i)" place="margin">Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> 
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Joh. 3.9. <hi>Euſeb. hiſt. eccl. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Diotrophes,</hi> 
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. eccl. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>29.</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Samoſatenus,</hi> &amp;c. Others out of covetouſneſſe, as <note n="(m)" place="margin">Ibid. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Natalius,</hi> and thoſe in the <note n="(n)" place="margin">Tit. 1.11. Rom. 16.18.</note> Apoſtles times: And not a few out of diſcontent and revenge, as <note n="(o)" place="margin">Socr. ſchol. hiſt. eccl. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Apollinaris, Donatus, Marcion:</hi> Some of little learning, but more then ſufficient boldneſſe, as <hi>Aetius,</hi> and very many doting dreamers; and others whoſe braines he had garriſon'd and maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined for his own uſe, full fraughting them with Philoſophy, and unſubmitted principles to higher truths, as <hi>Valentinus, Photinus,</hi> with divers others. And by theſe huckſters he drove ſo great a trade, that no few cuſtomers were gained by them: ſo that Haereſie in many places might well boaſt againſt truth, as <hi>Theodata</hi> in <hi>Aelian</hi> againſt the Philoſopher, That her followers far exceeded the number of his.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat. 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 11.</note> Chriſt, before his death, predicted it ſhould be ſo, <hi>That many falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets ſhould after his departure ariſe, and deceive many.</hi> 
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">2 Tim. 3 6.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his time ſaw them like ſome terrible tempeſt or horrid Harocan, <note n="(r)" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.18</note> ſubverting whole houſes, overthrowing the faith of many. <note n="(s)" place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. eccl. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> S. <hi>John</hi> who lived the longeſt, ſees <hi>Cerinthus, Menander,</hi> and <hi>Ebion,</hi> againſt whoſe haereſie he writes his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114059:14"/>
and foreſees in Prophetick viſion the <note n="(t)" place="margin">Rom. 13.3</note> Beaſt who pretends to be <hi>Chriſts</hi> Vicar, the ſucceeding dragon of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; all the earth wandring after him. And in later times, was ever that Counteſſe more fruitfull in her prodigious birth of three hundred ſixty and four children at one time (if the <hi>Holland</hi>-ſtory abuſe us nor) then theſe pernicious Errors have been in ſundry places? witneſſe <hi>Poland,</hi> and the neighbouring Territories, abounding with <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians,</hi> and other haereſies of all ſorts and ſizes; <hi>Germany,</hi> famous for fruitfulneſſe in miſ-ſhapen monſtrous Opinions; The <hi>Low-Countries</hi> have not been much behind the forementioned places for fertility in theſe noyſome weeds; And now at laſt poor <hi>England</hi> hath too large a ſhare in the ſad infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and ſpreading of this deſperate Malady: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the increaſe of <hi>Familiſme, Antinomianiſme, Socinianiſme,</hi> and many other deſperate Tenets, ſo far prevailing amongſt the People, that except ſome ſpeedy courſe be taken to prevent their further ſpreading, they threaten a terrible inundation, to the loſſe of Truth, and utter ruine of the Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But may ſome ſay;   Seeing the wayes of Error are full of waſting, deſtruction, and of ſo deformed a ſhape and ugly viſage in themſelves, how come they to be ſo prevalent with many, ſo that not a few, but <hi>many</hi> are infected with them?</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 1. One reaſon for this may be,   The quality and condition of thoſe that broach and divulge them:<note place="margin">Reaſons of the ſpreading of Haereſies.</note> Either they are perſons of parts and learning, as <hi>Valentinus, Socinus, Simachus,</hi> and divers others: Or ſuch as are of reputed Piety; they have a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114059:15"/>
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.5.</note> form of godlines, and in their words and deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are transformed into <note n="(w)" place="margin">2 Cor. 11, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> Angels of light; as <hi>Montanus, Novatus, Arrius,</hi> the <hi>Munſter</hi>-Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, who in the beginning exceedingly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed by their diſcourſes, which were at the firſt of nothing but <note n="(x)" place="margin">Bulling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Anabap. l. <hi>2.</hi> c <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</hi>
               </note> Mortification, Faſting, and other Religious exerciſes; and their pretence in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portments was to more then ordinary piety: This made them to be indulged in ſome petty differences in Opinion, by thoſe that were in Authority; pitied by the chief reforming Miniſters; adhered to by many ſingle-hearted, but inadvertent pious people, who ſo much liſtned to and believed their words, and were ſo gull'd by their ſpecious ſhews, that they little dreamt of the miſchief that ſome of their ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders aimed at, or the progreſſe they intended to make, till many of them had brought themſelves into ſuch a trap, that there was ſcarce any hope or means left to them to evade a moſt deſperate and utter ruine: Thus, they having the repute of faire and conſcientious Dealers, could not want Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, who with too greedy a mind would receive and take upon truſt their Errors. But to cloſe this; There are many likewiſe, who have not only ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured, but ſuffered for Religion, whereby they have growne in eſtimation with well-meaning pious people: I might give many inſtances in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times hereof, but I omit them; take only an example of latter dayes.<note place="margin">Hiſt. David. George.</note> 
               <hi>David George,</hi> at firſt a citizen of <hi>Delph,</hi> was caſt into priſon, bored through the tongue for ſpeaking againſt and withſtanding Popiſh idolatry, by which he came to be in high eſteem with the godly; yet afterward became one
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114059:15"/>
of the worſt, and moſt blaſphemous Haereticks in any age of the Church I have read of, aſſerting the Scriptures, yea thoſe of the Apoſtles, were lame, childiſh, and ineffectuall for the underſtanding of the things of God; that he was greater then Chriſt in the fleſh, &amp;c. But by reaſon of his ſufferings for truth in former times, he was in ſo great repute, that he eaſily ſeduced many unſtable ſouls to become of his Opinions.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> 2.   There is much to be attributed to the way and manner of diſpencing of theſe pernicious Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. <note n="(z)" place="margin">Eph. 4.14.</note> They want not their guiles and arts to inſnare poor ſouls; They ſtudy the perſons, and wait their opportunity to deceive; <note n="(a)" place="margin">Rom. 16.18</note> They uſe fair ſpeeches to beguile the hearts of the ſimple; profeſſions of love and charity, To be eyes to the blind, feet to the lame, guides to the erring. Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſay they, <note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 7.4.</note> let me pull out the mote that is in thine eye. The wolf layes the ſheep, when he ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth on him, upon his back gently, as if he meant but only to eaſe him; whereas indeed his purpoſe is to take his opportunity that he may devoure him. So for all the ſheeps cloathing, yet are ſeducers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly but <note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 7.15.</note> ravening wolves. And becauſe they conceive, to lay open and rebuke the faults of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is no ſmall means to conceal their own, and render themſelves unſuſpected to thoſe they deale with; Therefore how do they curiouſly pry into the faults of others, and like fleſh flies paſſing over what's ſound and right, light only on what's ſore and putrid in them? <note n="(d)" place="margin">Flavian. epiſt. ad Leon. Pap.</note> 
               <hi>Eutyches</hi> confutes <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius,</hi> that he might gain repute to himſelf, and falſe opinion. Neither want they vehemency and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114059:16"/>
ejulation, confidence, boldneſſe, and reſolution, being men of a <note n="(e)" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.</note> ſeared conſcience, and brazen forehead, that cannot bluſh. To ſet their Errors home, and to commend them the better to thoſe they intend to make their diſciples, they practiſe the old trick of one of the prime perſons of their order, I mean <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> who to gain the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er repute of himſelf, and credit to his blaſphemies, perſwaded the poor Samaritans <note n="(f)" place="margin">Act. 8.9, 10.</note> that <hi>he was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body,</hi> no leſſe then the <hi>mighty power of God;</hi> which teſtimony of his being too eaſily believed by thoſe poor creatures, gaind the attention &amp; reſpect of <hi>ſmal and great in that place to him.</hi> After him <note n="(g)" place="margin">Jactabat ſacram Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam ſe ſolum &amp; primum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligece. <hi>Vinc. Lyr. c. 42</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> trod in his ſteps of pride, boaſting, That he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone knew the meaning of the Scriptures, and was the firſt that rightly underſtood them. And this hath been from time to time the ſtrain of theſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, to caſt out <note n="(h)" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.18. Jude 26.</note> ſwelling words of vanity, whereby they gained on weak mindes ſufficiently, who uſe to judge of doctrines, rather by the conceit they have of the perſon that vents them, then by their conformity to the Word of truth. So <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomius</hi> likewiſe boaſted, That he knew God with the ſame knowledge wherewithall God knew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. They pretend to high <note n="(i)" place="margin">Col. 2.18.</note> myſteries and depths, being vainly puft up in their carnal minds, intruding themſelvs into things they underſtand not; &amp; have anſwerably their canting language, which may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther amaze their auditors, and lead them into miſts of darkneſſe and giddineſſe, then into the leaſt true notion of heavenly truth. They leave not here, but that their Authority may be beyond all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioning, <note n="(k)" place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. eccl. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> They boaſt of the preſcriptions of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114059:16"/>
Apoſtles, and the prime Pillars of Chriſtianity: So did the Haereticks of old, and the Papiſts ſtill to this day with great impudencie; but ſcarce ſo much as any colour of truth, except it be fetcht out of ſpurious writings and legends falſly attributed to thoſe holy men, and nothing agreeing with their genuine writings. But, becauſe Divine teſtimony is of higheſt authority, and moſt infallible, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will rather father blaſphemouſly their Errors on the Spirit of truth, then not gain belief; <note n="(l)" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16.</note> either wracking or wreſting his Word to their purpoſe, abuſing the Scriptures; or elſe they will boaſt (if no warrant, ſo much as ſeemingly probable, can be found in His book for their unworthy aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and practiſes) that they have their direction from immediate Revelation and Inſpiration; as the <hi>Montaniſts</hi> of old; and not long ſince, <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> and his followers at <hi>Munſter,</hi> for their abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable doctrine and lothſome courſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The matter they broach, is no ſmall cauſe and reaſon of their ſo much prevailing with multitudes. For perhaps it is ſomething New, ſuch with which they have not had the leaſt acquaintance before: now naturally men have <note n="(m)" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.5.</note> itching eares, are true <note n="(n)" place="margin">Act. 17.21.</note> Athenians greedy of new things; They are quickly weary of old Truths, becauſe they never ſaw their beauty, nor taſted their ſweetneſſe by an intuitive knowledge; for if they had, they would have found ſuch pleaſure and profit in them, as not to have been at all weary of them; Truths beauty alwayes laſting as freſh as at her firſt appearance to us, and alway ſpringing gloriouſly in greeneſſe and pleaſant fruits, not capable of being ſlighted by the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114059:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:114059:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:114059:18"/>
ſoul that knows her. But what if (as it fals out too often) theſe new Truths prove but old Errors new varniſht over? As in theſe giddy times wherein we live, who would not almoſt give credit to that old Pythagorean fable, of mens ſouls paſſing when they die, into other bodies? There are ſome do ſo much reſemble <hi>Arrius, Donatus,</hi> the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> and other ancient Haereticks; that were we not aſſured the ſame Power of darkneſſe that acted the former, ſtill living, is vigorous in theſe alſo to the ſame ends and purpoſes, or elſe we might ſuppoſe the ſouls of the former haereticks had taken up the bodies of the latter for their dwellings.</p>
            <p>And many times, I muſt needs confeſſe, it is not ſo much new matter, as a new dreſſe in new-found language and unintelligible words, when they moſt boaſt of new Lights &amp; Doctrines, which <hi>Paul</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Tim. 6.20</note> counſels <hi>Timothy</hi> to ſhun and avoid. So that we may truly ſay concerning many of their Ringleaders in our dayes, as an Hiſtorian ſpeaks of the <hi>Ligurians</hi> of old, who dwelt amongſt bogs and buſhy places, <note n="(p)" place="margin">Major erat aliquanto labor invenire quam vincere.</note> That it was a greater labour to find them out, then to conquer them; So theſe men, they have ſuch gypſie, fuſtian Language, in which they endeavour to lie hid, and conceal their ſenſe and meaning, for fear that if they ſhould come to the light, it would quickly appear what adulterate ſtuffe they endeavour to obtrude for Goſpel upon poor ſouls; therefore it is their pretence, That what they ſpeak is <note n="(q)" place="margin">Deſiderant ut iniquitas eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſit myſticae, religionis nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne palliata. <hi>Anſelm.</hi>
               </note> myſtical, rather to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by an implicite faith, and adored with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, then pryed into by reaſon, or examined by comparing it with the Law and Teſtimony, to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114059:18"/>
which <note n="(r)" place="margin">Eſay 8.20.</note> God ſends his people. Yet I muſt needs acknowledge alſo, that many times there are ſome of this ſeduceing crue, who run as much wild on the other hand, endevouring to bring down Religion in the higheſt myſteries thereof to the ſcanning and judgement of humane reaſon; <note n="(s)" place="margin">
                  <p>Credere ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid eſſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quod ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio non poteſt apprehendere, nec intellectus intelligere, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatis ſignum eſſe dicimus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Averroes,</hi> qui ſubinde chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is ogganiebat. ſic <hi>Socinus,</hi> &amp; multi haeretici, &amp;c.</p>
               </note> and what fals not within the approbation of this, they reject as ſpuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Hence came the <hi>Antitrinitarian</hi> error; the opinion of the death of ſouls; the deniall of the bodies reſurrection, and the like. <note n="(t)" place="margin">Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas haeretico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. <hi>Tertull.</hi> lib. cont. <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mog.</hi>
               </note> Hence <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> rightly ſtiles the Philoſophers, <hi>the patriarchs or heads of haereticks.</hi> And becauſe they will not faile to overcome, and prevaile with the people; it is not the leaſt part of their care, and cunning, to proportion their doctrine, and ſhape their tenets to the peoples humour; they propheſie <note n="(u)" place="margin">Eſay 30.10</note> 
               <hi>ſmooth things,</hi> and <note n="(x)" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.19</note> 
               <hi>promiſe them liberty,</hi> as <note n="(y)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb.</hi> lib. <hi>4</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi> hiſt. Eccl.</note> 
               <hi>Barcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chebas</hi> did the inſlaved Jewes, or life and ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity from death and evils <note n="(z)" place="margin">Juſt. Mart. <hi>Apol.</hi> 2. <hi>pro Chriſt.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Menander</hi> the haereticall ſorcerer did to his diſciples; hereby they take with the people, who cry them up for ſweet Goſpel Preachers, their new light beſt agreeing with the carnall affections, and earthly deſigns and reſolutions of their fleſhly auditors: Lyes, like can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle-light, beſt ſerving to ſet off the maſques and mummeries of the world, whereas the <note n="(a)" place="margin">Eph. 5.23.</note> bright day-light of heavenly truth would mar all. Yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if they ſhould diſcover themſelves in a conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t divulging of new and ſtrange opinions, it might ſtartle the people they deale with, and make them more cautious how they give up their ſpirits to be leveaned by them; therefore they have got this trick and ſlight, to hold forth ſome known truths,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114059:19"/>
which managing to their own advantage, they make the means to attract the belief of the people the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to what they ſhall afterwards hold forth of their own unto them. Somewhat <note n="(e)" place="margin">Strabo. <hi>lib.</hi> 15.</note> like the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ape-catching in the <hi>Indies.</hi> The perſon that watches to take that creature, firſt brings a baſon or veſſell of pure water; which when the ape per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives (the man being retired out of ſight) down comes hee, and having gaz'd on himſelfe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held his face in the water a while, hee begins to dab, and waſh himſelfe therein; which when hee hath done ſufficiently, hee gets up into the tree again; which when the man perceives, hee takes away the baſon or veſſell of water, inſtead thereof conveying a veſſell of bird-lime; the poor ape ſuſpecting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, the heat prevailing over the waters refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing coldneſſe, comes down from the tree again, and fals to patting of himſelfe about the face and head as before; by which his eyes being clos'd with the bird-lime, hee becomes a prey to his wily catcher. So hath it been, nay is at this preſent day with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeducers amongſt us, &amp;c. They know that their doctrine like adulterate coyne could not paſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe there were ſome mixture of the gold or ſilver of truth with their baſer mettal of error; therefore they gild over their more horrible opinions with Orthodox truths, or at the leaſt with ſuch expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as ſeem to ordinary capacities to be very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and little or nothing different from the minde of the Church of Chriſt, when in truth they mean nothing leſſe: But <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Geſner.</hi> hiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Plin.</hi> lib. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> as the fiſh called <hi>Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie,</hi> or by ſome the Sea-clerk, when hee is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be taken, caſts forth an inky black ſubſtance,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114059:19"/>
in which concealing himſelf from the ſight of the fiſher, in that night of darkneſſe he paſſes away undiſcovered and evades the danger. Even ſo do theſe Seducers eſcape the being diſcovered what they are, by their dark expreſſions and ambiguous words, which either are not underſtood, or elſe in them they ſeem to many, that they ſpeak but the ſame things with us (as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſays) when indeed they mean nothing leſſe then truth:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Iraen.</note> whereby it comes to paſſe, that even as poyſon given in honey enters the veines quickly, and piercing the deeper, kills the ſpeedier, and more ſurely; ſo their deſperate Errors being covered in the <note n="(g)" place="margin">Rom. 16.18</note> pleaſing words of ſeeming and approved Verity, are entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Peoples mind with approbation, and there received as the truth of God with greateſt liking, and held faſt with ſo much obſtinacie, that (as we ſee by ſad experience) <note n="(h)" place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note> they reckon them their ſoreſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that tell them the truth, nay will rather periſh than ſuffer theſe cords of death to be taken from them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fault many times is much in the <note n="(i)" place="margin">Mat. 13 25</note> ſervants whom Chriſt hath imployed about his vineyard, to take care that the ſeed of wholſome Truth be ſown, and every plant that is contrary thereunto of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious mans planting, according to the power where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath betruſted them, eradicated and plucked up. The Miniſter in his ſphere, by <note n="(k)" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.2, &amp;c.</note> frequent Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, holding forth the whole truth of God cleerly, <note n="(l)" place="margin">Tit. 1.9.</note> confuting gainſayers ſolidly, if after two or three admonitions they refuſe to be gained, <note n="(m)" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.16, 17.</note> avoiding and ſhunning their perverſe diſputes, and company, warning others to beware of them; <note n="(n)" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.24, 25, 26.</note> uſing all gentleneſſe and patience to them that are ſeduced,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114059:20"/>
               <hi>proving if God at any time will give them repentance, that they may eſcape out of this ſnare of the devil.</hi> And if all will not do, but ſtill this gangrene ſpreads, and threatens ruine to the whole; <note n="(n)" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.20.</note> Then ought they to exerciſe that dreadfull Cenſure of the Church; that neither this <note n="(o)" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.6, 7.</note> leaven for want of caſting out may ſoure the lump, nor <note n="(p)" place="margin">Heb 12.15</note> this root of bitterneſſe ſo ſpread, by being amongſt the profeſſors of verity, as that many ſhould be perverted thereby; nor they be partakers of Seducers ſins, by an unrighteous ſilence, of unjuſt with-holding that Ordinance of GOD, which poſſibly may tend to the making even the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer ſenſible of his crime, by Gods bleſſing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence; but however, it is like to put a ſtand to their madneſſe, make others <note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.20.</note> fear, and be very cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, how either they receive their doctrine whom the Church of Chriſt declares deceivers, or run their courſe which may bring them into the ſame condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation with theſe their ſeducing guides. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the Miniſters of Chriſt have diſcharged their duty, and may have much peace and comfort therein, whatever the event and iſſue thereof prove to be.</p>
            <p>There is another ſervant whom Chriſt hath intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this great buſineſſe, and that is the Magiſtrate; Although there be <note n="(r)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Stapleton,</hi> in Relect. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trov. <hi>2.</hi> queſt. <hi>5.</hi> art. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>253. Bellarm.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> de R. P. cap. <hi>7. Tannerus, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus,</hi> cum multis aliis.</note> ſome that would limit and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain his power to ſecular affairs: yet is this doctrine ſo little anſwerable either to the practiſe of moſt pious <note n="(s)" place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Chron. 23. 1 Chr. 31. 2 King 23.</hi> Vos eſtis epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi in eccleſia; ego extra eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam ſeu tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plure epiſcopus à Deo ſum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutus. <hi>Euſeb.</hi>
               </note> Governours, to the opinion of <note n="(t)" place="margin">
                  <p>Aug. epiſt. <hi>50.</hi> ad Bonif. ep. <hi>48</hi> ad Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. l. <hi>3.</hi> cont. Creſc. gram. c. <hi>51.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Leo epiſt. <hi>9.</hi> ad Theodoſ. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Antiquity, or to <note n="(u)" place="margin">Deut. 17.18. <hi>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> 2 King. 11.12. 1 Tim. 2.1, 2. Rom. 13.1, &amp;c. Eſa. 49.23.</note> Scripture verity; that were not theſe men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly ignorant, or exceedingly impudent, they would never maintain an opinion ſo plainly oppoſite to truth as this is. But alas, here is the ſad root of this miſery: That either the Miniſters are <note n="(x)" place="margin">Iſa. 56.10.</note> igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114059:20"/>
and unable to maintain the truth, confute and ſtop the mouths of gainſayers; or they are wicked and ſcandalous, like <note n="(y)" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Elies</hi> ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, whoſe prophane and ungodly courſes loſe all repute to the Truth, making the things of God (by thoſe who meaſure truth by the lives and carriages of them that maintain it) to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned and abhorred. If neither of theſe, yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they are <note n="(z)" place="margin">Rev. 2.20.</note> careleſſe, negligent, &amp; inadvertent, nothing heeding how Truth thrives, or how Error ſpreads, as if to them it were of very ſmall or no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment: In point of benefit they are greedy dogs, zealous enough for their profit, <note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſa. 56.11.</note> looking after that from every quarter; but in point of duty they want heat, <note n="(b)" place="margin">Rev. 3.15.</note> the fire of zeal for Gods glory is not in them, therefore they love their eaſe, to ſleep, ſlumber, and take their reſt; whereby they give not only an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to the Evil one to ſow his tares, but to thoſe tares to take root and proſper.</p>
            <p>Or laſtly; They are magiſteriall and proud, teſty and froward, whereas they ought to be <note n="(c)" place="margin">Gal. 6.1.</note> lowly and meek, <note n="(d)" place="margin">2 Tim. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 24, 25.</note> gentle towards all, apt to teach, waiting with patience: but this their courſe and carriage is no ſmall means to alienate poor ſeduced ſouls from the truth, making them believe that truth hath but ſmall ſtrength of reaſon and wiſdome to ſupport it, and therefore ſtands in need of the weak and loathſome props of Pride and paſſion. Thus verity is diſgraced. But, many times the Miniſter may do his duty, and yet by reaſon of the Magiſtrates miſcarriage theſe Haereſies may flouriſh; becauſe, perhaps, they have conquered himſelf: Now <note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal 11.3.</note> if the <hi>foundations be removed, what then can the righteous do?</hi> O how ſad was the Churches condition, when Emperours, Kings
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114059:21"/>
and Governours were infected with the Arrian haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; when <hi>Arrianiſme</hi> 
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Vincent. Lyr. cont. haereſ.</note> like a helliſh fury, laid hold on the Throne it ſelf; the People imitating and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming to their Princes judgement and manners, were quickly and eaſily infected with it. Or ſuppoſe they be not tainted themſelves, yet if they be irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and profane, who make as ſlight of differences in Religion, as <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 25.19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>Feſtus</hi> did in the buſineſſe of <hi>Paul;</hi> Or timorous to diſpleaſe, of a low and inferior ſpirit, ſlothfull to erract, or execute according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merit of the Error, or the Haeretick; how can it from ſuch be expected, either that Truth ſhould be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or a ſtop put to the madneſſe of people by them?</p>
            <p n="5">5. This is too often occaſioned through the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous differences in Judgement about things not much material, that are amongſt different Miniſters and Profeſſors of Piety and Religion, whereby they are ſo divided in affection and exaſperated againſt each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that their bitter words and carriages too often diſcover that fire of hell which burns within, though at the ſame time they agree in fundamentals, and things that are abſolutely neceſſary to eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. There are no few examples of this might be given in Primitive times; <note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt eccl. l. <hi>5</hi> c. 21, &amp;c</note> as about the time of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> maintained with no ſmall heat, and ſuch like petty dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences breaking forth by degrees into horrid flames. The like hath too much happened in the Church of Chriſt in latter times: The Miniſters and Profeſſors of Religion not long ſince in this Iſland, were like a goodly Mirrour, all of one peece, glorious in truth and piety, by reaſon of the bright beams of the Sunne of Righteouſneſſe, that Fountain of true light and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114059:21"/>
ſhining on them: But oh how are they broken all to ſhivers, and who can expreſſe the ſad conſequents of their diſſentions! The Profane are detetred from looking towards Religion, becauſe they conceive it to be a thing of ſo great uncertainty, that it will be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for them to attain to any aſſurance of what is truth, ſeeing ſuch perſons of parts and piety cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree about it. The weak, contrary to the Apoſtles <note n="(f)" place="margin">Rom. 14.1.</note> canon, being received to doubtfull diſputations, or hearing ſo much of differences amongſt thoſe that are reckoned more then ordinary in Religion, lie down in deſpondencie of ſpirit, and are ſubjected to ſad temptations of misbelief and error: That which <note n="(g)" place="margin">Heb. 12.13.</note> halts, in ſtead of being healed is clean turn'd out of the way of truth: The ſtrong are grieved; and the Devil laughs to ſee his work go forward, his kingdom increaſe, his tares ſo readily entertained, by the means of thoſe whom he lookt upon as his moſt mortall enemies.</p>
            <p n="6">6. All the former cauſes of the growth of haereſie would not be effectually operative, were it not that Peoples hearts are like a prepared ſoile, ready to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain theſe damnable errors. Look into their minds, they are filled with darkneſſe; how then ſhould they be able to underſtand, or judge of the things of God? they cannot, <note n="(h)" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</note> for <hi>they are ſpiritually diſcerned,</hi> in heavenly light, only manifeſt to an enlightned mind; all colours in the dark are alike. Neither is this only Naturall, but adventitious; frequently from a cold frozen heart void of Truths love, which like cold weather thickens the clouds, cauſing darkneſſe; and darkneſſe prevailing by the clouds being thickned, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114059:22"/>
the cold: ſo is it here: A cold frozen ſpirit clouds and darkens the mind; and the mind being darkned, heighthens and increaſes the coldneſſe and benummedneſſe of the heart, in reſpect of that affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which it owes to the truth. But yet in many, (bleſſed be God) there are beginning of Knowledge; which in moſt of theſe being but very beginnings and embrioes of Truth, they hang too <note n="(i)" place="margin">Act 26 28.</note> equally ballanced between it and error, being full of doubtfulneſſe, and are not freed from jealouſies and ſuſpitions, <note n="(k)" place="margin">Mar. 13.21</note> which are apt to take fire, break forth and ſhew themſelves, when Seducers queſtion the truths they pretend to hold, but in truth are far from any firm and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate aſſent upon any right ground; which makes them ſo eaſily let them ſlip, and barter them for ſuch coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit ware as theſe ſoul-deſtroying Errors be. They are very credulous, like <note n="(l)" place="margin">Prov. 14.25.</note> Solomons fool, perhaps many times out of <note n="(m)" place="margin">Taedio in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtigandae pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus veritatis, cuilibet opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oni potius ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbere maliit quàm in explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando pertinaci diligentia per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverare. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut. in Octav.</hi> Malunt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere quàm ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicare. <hi>Sen.</hi>
               </note> ſlothfull ſluggiſhneſſe, being rather willing to take what they hear on truſt, then to trouble themſelves and take pains about it, to try what conformity and proportion it holds with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring, undeceiving Word of truth, the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Many have corrupt Conſciences, that muſt be <note n="(n)" place="margin">Ezek. 13.18, 20</note> boulſtered <note n="(o)" place="margin">2 Tim. 4 3.</note> corrupt Affections, that muſt be humoured; corrupt Practiſes, that muſt be like ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes concealed and hid. This will make them, like the Elephant, to mud the pure water of the doctrine of truth, that they may not ſee and be convinced of their uglineſſe; as the <note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat. 5.21, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Phariſees did the Law by their fooliſh gloſſes.</p>
            <p>Corrupt and pervert the Truth, that they may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void torture of Conſcience. When the <hi>Athenians</hi> had loſt <hi>Salmis,</hi> they made a law againſt the naming of it:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114059:22"/>
So, whatever may torment them before their time, they rather flatly deny it, or ſome falſe way or other they take to avoid the force and conviction thereof. Witneſſe thoſe people in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> that began to ſay, There is <note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.12.</note> no Reſurrection. <note n="(r)" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Himi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> that affirmed it was already paſt. Indeed they could wiſh it were ſo, becauſe of its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, The laſt Judgement; which doctrine, if they ſhould rightly conſider, would make them <note n="(s)" place="margin">Act 24.25.</note> tremble: therefore they chuſe that doctrine to maintain, which may beſt ſute with their credit and reputation, peace and quietneſſe, <note n="(t)" place="margin">Joh. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>They love darkneſſe more then light, becauſe their works are evil.</hi> 
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">1 King. 22.8.</note> 
               <hi>Michaiah</hi> is too plain and tart, <hi>He ſpeaks no good concerning me,</hi> ſayes wicked <hi>Ahab.</hi> 
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">Mat. 5.13.</note> The ſalt of truth, though it hath wholſomneſſe, yet hath it tartneſſe in it, which they will not endure. <note n="(y)" place="margin">Strabo l <hi>17.</hi> num. <hi>565.</hi>
               </note> The <hi>Aethiopians</hi> curſe the Sun when it riſes, becauſe it ſcorches them. <note n="(z)" place="margin">Rev. 11.10</note> The Earth cannot beare the two Witneſſes, becauſe they vex the inhabitants thereof: So doth Truth the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ſpirits of theſe people, <note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.18.</note> therefore they are very willing to entertain that which may better agree with their frame and temper of ſpirit, with their carnal tranquility of mind and <note n="(a)" place="margin">Mich. 2.11</note> wayes which they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to walk in; and making their luſts their law, <note n="(b)" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.18</note> lie open to be ſeduced by ſuch who bait their hook with what is proportionable to thoſe luſts in them. Yet perhaps they may pretend, that they ſeek for, and love the Truth; which certainly if they did, they would make it more their buſineſſe to be acquainted with it, and would not let it lie ſo careleſly and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially on the ſurface of their ſouls without any watch or guard upon it, <note n="(c)" place="margin">Luk. 8.5.</note> like the ſeed on the high-way
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:114059:23"/>
There are too too many who are ſo greedy of New lights, that old truths will not down: They are like the old <note n="*" place="margin">Sceptici philoſophi qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi quaeſitores &amp; conſideratores, qui omnia in ſuſpenſo relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes, nihil definiunt. <hi>Gell. l. 15. c. 5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Scepticks,</hi> accounting it no ſmall bondage to fixe a belief of any truth almoſt, but delight in a vagrancie of mind without law or limit. And to make their miſery compleat, they are ſo unhappy as to fall in love with their own underſtanding ſo farre, as to make it the ſoveraign Judge of controverſies, and Rule of truth, contrary to the adviſe of <note n="(e)" place="margin">Prov. 3, 5.28, 26. 1 Cor. 3.18. 2 Cor. 10.5.</note> Scriptures: by which means, becauſe their mind is full of <note n="(f)" place="margin">Eph. 5.3. 2 Pet. 2.18. Jude 16, 18, 19. 2 Pet. 3.3.</note> dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and erroneous principles, naturally being byaſſed by perverſe and carnal affection, which mould and modelize their apprehenſions; therefore they cannot chuſe but erre, and miſtake in their choice, and deciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of truth and error. Many times like the <hi>Abiſſines,</hi> who becauſe they are black, when they picture Angels they draw them in the ſame colour with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Even ſo do theſe; whatever is tendred to them, if it agree with their humour and fancie, they imbrace and cry it up for truth. Now therefore theſe things being duly conſidered, it is no great wonder, though not a <hi>few,</hi> but <hi>Many</hi> are perverted by Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers.</p>
            <p n="7">7. We may adde to the former reaſons, very often, the concurrence of the time and ſeaſon, which very much conduces to help forward this evil. Perhaps it is a time of Liberty, ſuch a ſeaſon wherein the reines of Government are laid too looſely upon the Peoples neck; Nay, perhaps the garb and faſhion that is moſt in requeſt, is Haereſie: which finding patronage from perſons of no mean rank, and encouragement, no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell though it ſpread apace and flouriſh. Flies, Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and ſuch like creatures, remain as dead in the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114059:23"/>
Winter; and Weeds appeare not, till the Summers ſun revive and draw them forth: ſo Errors, if they received not ſome gleams of countenance, or at leaſt connivence from ſome of a ſuperior Orbe, would (in all probability) ſoon dwinder, and quickly vaniſh.</p>
            <p n="8">8. 'Tis Gods juſt judgement on them who <note n="(g)" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.11.</note> receive not his Truth in the love thereof, to give them up to the <note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſal. 81.11</note> writhings of their own hearts to walk in their own counſels; to ſend them ſtrong deluſion to believe a lye; to deliver them up to Satan, who hath power to ſeduce and capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate thoſe whom God deſerts and leaves. But we muſt rightly conceive of this; that God is not the cauſe efficiently, for he is not the author of what he is the revenger; But as a righteous Judge, he gives liberty to that Arch-enemy of mankinde to tempt; with-holds or denies that grace, through the preſence of which they might be ſecured againſt his fiery darts; nay many times withdrawes the grace they have, which did back-biaſſe Natures in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to ſuch or ſuch an Error; which rub be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once removed, the temptations of theſe haereſies here mentioned, too eaſily prevail. And thus you ſee how Haereſies come to captivate, not a few, but <hi>many,</hi> as in this Text.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> O how ſad a ſight is it in your thoughts,   to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the ſpreading of this infection, the ſhoales that being perverted follow theſe pernicious wayes: <note n="(i)" place="margin">Mat. 13.38</note> to ſee how faſt theſe Tares thrive, this <note n="(k)" place="margin">Mat. 16.11 1 Cor. 5.8.</note> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſpreads, this <note n="(l)" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.17.</note> Gangrene frets! The Kingdom looks like a Lazar-houſe, or field fought in many
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114059:24"/>
places, by reaſon of this: How many are there of all ages inſnared by them? The hoary head that is ready to deſcend to the grave; and your hopefull Spring, that ſeemed to promiſe life and happineſſe to Church and State; Almoſt all ranks and degrees have felt the poiſonous blaſts of damnable Error; which like that haile in the <note n="(m)" place="margin">Rev. 8.7. <hi>Gerhard. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc.</hi> 8.7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Revelation,</hi> hath ſmitten tall trees, as well as low graſſe; by <hi>trees</hi> ſome underſtanding perſons of power and place, by <hi>graſſe</hi> inferior people. Nay, this miſchief hath lighted not only upon the Prophane, to be rid of whom the Church and State might be glad, as wennes, ſores, and putrid members, except they would mend; but alſo upon Profeſſors of godlineſſe, that have looked ore-night like an early ripe apple, yelow &amp; red above the reſt, yet in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning have been <note n="(n)" place="margin">Gal. 5.7, &amp;c 3.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> found under the tree; this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed Haereſie hath thrown them out of their place: truth is, there is cauſe to fear that ſome worm, ſome boſome-ſin or other hath devoured their moiſture within, whereby they are viſibly the ſooner ripe, but indeed rotten. So that you have cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of divers, as <note n="(o)" place="margin">Euſeb. vita Conſt.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtantine</hi> did of many in his time, That thoſe by whom he hoped to have cured others, were brainſick themſelves, and needed cure. Nor are there amongſt theſe <hi>Many</hi> only an ignorant rout, but men of excellent naturall endowments, and tolerable acquired abilities: Alas, the temple of the Church is full of ſmoak, the ſhip of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth is full of water, All is on fire. Oh the ſad cries from many parts of the Kingdome to you! If there be any help in your hand, (ſay they) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label> 
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:114059:24"/>But why (may ſome ſay) all this ado?   'Tis no new thing, but uſuall in time of Reformation, to be troubled with Errors; was it not ſo, not only in the Primitive time, but alſo when <hi>Luther</hi> and others were ſtirred up to purge Gods floor? What ſhoals of Haereticks were raiſed up by hell to blaſt their work, and render it odious to the world, as if it were a ſeed producing monſters and enormities, rather then reducing things to Primitive purity and regularity?</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 1. I know and confeſſe indeed,   the <note n="(p)" place="margin">Mark. 9.26.</note> Devil moſt roars and rends when he is caſting out, and expreſſes moſt rage when he <note n="(q)" place="margin">Rev. 12.12</note> feeles his paſſion drawing on, becauſe hee knowes his time is ſhort.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But yet, I hope our Reformation is not in Fundamentals: we have long enjoyed as cleer light, &amp; as full diſcoveries of fundamental truths, as any Church that I know under the cope of heaven; Others have gladly lighted their tapers more at our flame, then we at theirs. And oh, what ſober reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſpirit bleeds not to ſee, that after the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this bleſſed Sun-ſhine for more then four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore years, not a <hi>few,</hi> but <hi>many</hi> ſhould be ſeduced to run ſo willingly, ſwiftly, furiouſly, obſtinately, into ſuch deſperate Errors?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> O worthy Senators, I beſeech you help, help.   You cannot anſwer as the King of Iſrael to the cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out complaining woman, <note n="(r)" place="margin">2 King. 6.26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>Whence ſhall I help thee?</hi> for God hath furniſhed you with power, are you not the Supreme Court? And hath ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened your hand with deliverance, ſubduing your enemies under you. Doth not the Church and State
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114059:25"/>
repoſe in you as Phyſitians of skill, and will? Oh deceive not their truſt, fruſtrate not their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Spend not their Coyn and Blood, and yet leave them in a more dangerous Labyrinth then where you found them, in point of Haereſie. Before they were afflicted by Men in the ſhape of beaſts, Perſons of Learning, parts, and birth; But now by Beaſts in the ſhape of men, Muſhromes, the birth of one night and darkneſſe; Of whom many could wiſh, that the courſe which <note n="*" place="margin">Socrat. ſchol. hiſt. eccleſ. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Julian</hi> took with the Chriſtians, might be yours, To ſhut up the Schools of Learning, that all might be reduced to the ſame degree of Barbariſme with themſelves. Oh how can you endure to ſee ſuch Troops ingulf themſelves in ruine? Hath not <hi>Salus populi,</hi> the Peoples ſafety, been your profeſſion? What, is it only of the Sheaf, and not the Soul? and that of no ſtrangers neither, but of thoſe that breath in the ſame Climate with you, live on the ſame ſoyle, are governed by the ſame Law, have the ſame Name, profeſſe the ſame Religion, pretend to the ſame GOD. Nor can you certainly forget, and ſo be cruell to yout own bowels. <note n="*" place="margin">Fincel. l. <hi>1.</hi> de miraculis. Lovic. Theat. hiſt. in praecept. quart. Manlii loc. com. cum multis al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> There be many reverend Authors tell a ſtrange ſtory that fell out at <hi>Hammel</hi> in <hi>Saxony,</hi> viz. That there came one in the ſhape of a Piper in a patcht pide coat, who when he firſt piped made all the Rats and Mice leave their holes and follow him out of the Town; but when he came again and piped, troops of the Citizens Children followed him dancing, till comming to a mountain not far from the city, the mountain open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and neither he nor they were ever ſeen after. Hath not this pyde piper <hi>Haereſie,</hi> perhaps led thoſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114059:25"/>
that are neare and deare unto you, you know not whither? Is it not dangerous to ſuffer Rats-bane to lie in ſight, or Conduit-heads to be poiſoned? May it not be juſt that thy wife or children ſhould be the next that are poiſoned by it? Is it not juſt, that ſuch as make it not their buſineſſe to maintain Truth in Gods houſe, ſhould have no peace in their own? What a ſad ſight will it be, to ſee thy poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in hell through thy negligence?</p>
            <p>Honoured Senators, give me leave to ſay, That if Poſterities care be an intangling argument when death comes, making men deſire life for their ſakes; certainly it never was more prevalent with wiſe and affectionate Parents, then at this time; wherein, if death takes us away, we are like to leave them (without Heavens protection) to be a prey to the worſt of miſchiefs, theſe damnable Errors. What profit, I beſeech you, is it, if now you have foiled our Enemies, the worſt of enemies foile ours, and lead them captive into a worſe captivity, then that of the body is or can be? In Plague-time you are carefull to keep the ſound and ſick aſunder, you have appointed diſtinguiſhing marks and badges: And in this worſt of plagues, will you ſuffer them to herd together?</p>
            <p>Have pity, I beſeech you, on the Church of God abroad, whoſe affliction it will be to ſee, and danger to feel the ſad effects of Haereſie, if like that woman in the <note n="*" place="margin">Zach. 5.11.</note> Prophet, it be ſuffered to build for it ſelf a houſe in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have pity, I beſeech you, on the Church of God at home; Once the greateſt eye-ſore to Haereticks, envy of Papiſts, refuge to the Orthodox, glorious
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114059:26"/>
for Doctrine, a praiſe in the Earth, the mother of many Stars of the firſt magnitude, famous Martyrs, faithfull Confeſſors, and innumerable ſoules in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Have compaſſion on your ſelves, your honour and reputation. Your outward and inward peace and tranquillity, your truth and fidelity under the profeſſion of ſo many Declarations, Remonſtrances and Ordinances, which I forbear to ſpecifie, are all deeply concerned in this.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, have pity upon, and I beſeech you ſhew mercy to lovely <hi>Truth,</hi> that beame of glory, daughter of heaven, <note n="(t)" place="margin">Pſal. 43.3.</note> that Clue of mercy let down into this dark erring World, to lead us through the many Labyrinths of a benighted Mind, erring Thoughts, miſleading Examples, dark Temptations, to bliſſe and happineſſe. For ſhe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, and is here like to periſh from us, and be utterly loſt, or at leaſt ſhrewdly ecclipſed, if you relieve her not: For, <hi>Through theſe the way of Truth is evil ſpoken of, or blaſphemed.</hi> And that is the Laſt part of the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Part </seg>3</label> In theſe words, <hi>By reaſon of whom the way of truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of</hi>— You have,</p>
            <p n="1">1. An epithete given to Chriſtian religion; 'tis ſtiled <hi>The way of truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The foul carriage of many wicked men to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it; <hi>It ſhall be blaſphemed, or evil ſpoken of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The cauſe and root of this miſchief; <hi>By rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of whom.</hi> Which words ſome referre to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers; but I rather, as agreeing beſt with the words and ſcope of the Apoſtle, with the moſt and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114059:26"/>
learnedſt Expoſitors referre it to the Seduced.</p>
            <p>But of each of theſe in their order; And firſt, very briefly of the firſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. An epithete given Religion, Tis <hi>the way of Truth.</hi> So ſtiled likewiſe by the <note n="(u)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.30. Pſal. 60.4.</note> Pſalmiſt, <hi>I have choſen</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the way of Truth.</hi> The <note n="(x)" place="margin">Iſa. 26.2. Jer. 9 3. Dan. 8.12.</note> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets very frequently give Religion this epithete; So likewiſe doe the bleſſed <note n="(y)" place="margin">2 Cor. 13.8. Gal. 3.1. James 5.19. 1 Pet. 1.22. Joh. 3.12.</note> Apoſtles, yea <note n="(z)" place="margin">Joh. 18.37.</note> Chriſt himſelf. It may well challenge this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious title,</p>
            <p>Firſt, from its parentage and originall, who is the <note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal 31.5. Rom. 3.4.</note> God of truth, the <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh. 14.6.</hi> Summa ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas nulli quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam debet, ſed omnia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent ci, &amp; ipſa eſt cauſa omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aliarum verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp;c. <hi>Anſel. de verit. Jam. 1.17.</hi>
               </note> firſt, infallible, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable, eternal Truth, the fountain of all kinds and degrees of truth, whether in this world, or that which is to come.</p>
            <p>Secondly, 'tis ſtiled <hi>the way of truth,</hi> by way of oppoſition to <note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.104.</note> lying falſhood and deceit. What ever other wayes and courſes pretend in reference to the making of us holy or happy, they are but ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wayes, not able to effect really in the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree what they hold forth to us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in reſpect of efficiencie, It not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires truth of us, but is Gods inſtrument whereby through the concurrence of his Spirit he works it in us, <note n="(d)" place="margin">Joh. 8.32. Pſal. 119.</note> freeing our minds from ſad deluding Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and our affections from every falſe deceiving way; thus working <note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſ. 51.6.</note> truth in the inward part, which he requires and delights in.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, in point of Termination; it brings thoſe that ſincerely imbrace and practiſe it, to the enjoyment of Truths fountain, the God of truth: being his way to us in point of communication and impartment; for he conveyes himſelf in his ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114059:27"/>
in beames of Truth to us, <note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 36 9.</note> 
               <hi>In his light we ſee light,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks: And 'tis our way to him; for <note n="(g)" place="margin">1 Joh. 1 7.</note> 
               <hi>if we walk in the light as he is light, we have communion one with another,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John.</hi> And thus briefly you ſee ſome few, of the many Reaſons that might be given, why Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is ſtiled <hi>The way of Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But ſecondly, See the courſe uſage Religion meets with from many in the world: It ſhall be <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> blaſphemed or evil ſpoken of, ſaith our Apoſtle; be uſed like him that is Truth it ſelf, in the dayes of his fleſh, <note n="(i)" place="margin">Luk. 2.34.</note> who was a ſigne that was ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, as S. <hi>Luke</hi> expreſſeth it. If I ſhould rake in the dunghill of the writing of Heathens, or repeat thoſe horrid words which they have uttered againſt the truth of God; or if I ſhould look into latter times, and mention thoſe baſe aſperſions, fooliſh ſcornes, ſcurrilous ſpeeches, that have been made uſe of by Atheiſtical ſpirits, dark-minded Pagans, or erring Papiſts, I might ſooner offend your eares, then want matter to inſiſt on.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How have profane ſpirits detracted from it, by decrying its birth and original to be ſo high and honourable as indeed it is? while they have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, <note n="(a)" place="margin">Act. 17.32.</note> That it is not of God, nor came down from heaven, but is the product of Mans brain, and that an ill one too; deſpoiling and deveſting it of all real value, as if there were (if their blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous ſpeeches might be believed) neither wiſdome, beauty, holineſſe, comfort, or happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be found in conforming to it. And the like.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:114059:27"/>2. There are many, who being acted by hell, have yet gone further; attributing to Religion ſuch things as are inconſiſtent with it, nay egregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly falſe, and directly oppoſite to the glory, nature, and being of it: as, That it came from hell; Takes with none but <note n="(b)" place="margin">Joh. 7.47, 48, 49.</note> baſe, ſhallow, fantaſtick people; That it makes thoſe that entertain it, proud, peeviſh, moroſe, <note n="(c)" place="margin">Act. 21 28, &amp;c.</note> rebellious, Libertines, unjuſt, and the like; That it will bring them to beggery, miſery, diſtraction, ſome violent death, and everlaſting ruine. Thus do they ſet their months againſt the God of heaven, while they bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheme his truth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There are others that yet go a ſtep further then the former, who do not only ſpeak evil of the Truth, but when they have rob'd Religion of her glory, they deck and adorne their doting, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Errors with Truths <note n="(d)" place="margin">Act 19 27, &amp;c. 35.</note> ornaments; attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting to them, as <hi>Numa</hi> and other deceivers to their Lawes, the title of Divine oracles, <note n="(e)" place="margin">Euſeb. eccl. hiſt. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Depths of wiſdome, Rules of piety, Saving truths, High and myſtical excellencies. Thus did <hi>Saturninus</hi> and divers others. He that would ſatisfie himſelf farther concerning theſe particulars, may take a view of <hi>Porphyrie's</hi> railing books againſt the Chriſtians; or later horrid Pamphlets exceeding his in blaſphemy, as that <hi>De tribus Impoſtoribus mundi;</hi> Popiſh railing libels; Haeretical writings, as that of <hi>Paul Beſt,</hi> The <hi>Mad-mans Divinity,</hi> and ſuch like ſtuffe.</p>
            <p>And thus briefly you ſee the truth of this ſecond particular, <hi>viz.</hi> The courſe uſage Religion meets with at the hands of ſome in the world, <hi>It is evil-ſpoken of or blaſphemed.</hi> But how comes this to paſs?
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114059:28"/>
Indeed it is mens baſeneſſe and prophaneſſe ſo to do; but yet there is ſeeming cauſe for it, which the Text holds forth in thoſe words, <hi>By reaſon of whom,</hi> i.e. of ſuch as are ſeduced. Which is the third and laſt Particular of this ſecond generall Part.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> A main cauſe and root of wicked mens blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming or ſpeaking evil of Religion, is, the following of Seducers by multitudes, who pretend to Truth, yet imbrace their pernicious wayes and errors.</p>
            <p>Thus was in the Primitive times the people who bare the name of Chriſtians, yet being ſeduced, profeſt ſuch doctrine as could no way agree with the Chriſtian verity, and walked in an anſwerable practiſe to their erroneous tenets, raiſed <note n="(f)" place="margin">Euſeb l. <hi>4.</hi> hist. eccl. c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> no ſmal perſecutions againſt the Church. For when the profane atheiſtical ſpirits of the world took notice in thoſe people either of their monſtrous and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd opinions, as that of <note n="(g)" place="margin">Epophan. haereſ. <hi>37.</hi> Aug. de haereſ.</note> the <hi>Ophites,</hi> who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the Serpent that ſeduced <hi>Eve,</hi> believing it was Chriſt: and the <note n="(h)" place="margin">Epiph. haer. <hi>38.</hi> Aug. de haer.</note> 
               <hi>Cainites,</hi> who honoured <hi>Cain</hi> as their father,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. eccl. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>26.</hi> Epiph. haereſ. <hi>21</hi> &amp; <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> highly eſteeming <hi>Eſau, Chore, Dathan, Abiran,</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> &amp;c. Their beaſtly tenets, as that of the <hi>Nicholaitans</hi> concerning com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of wives: or of the <hi>Simonians,</hi> concerning liberty to all licentiouſneſſe. Which when they take notice how contrary and oppoſite to Juſtice, Order, Modeſty, ſuch aſſertions are; this makes them taxe Religion as the Devils product, carrying ſouls headlong to eternall ruine. Or elſe they look upon their inconſtancy &amp; levity, frequently ſhifting opinions, and changing Sects, <note n="(k)" place="margin">Mat. 11.7.</note> like reeds ſhaken to and fro, or empty <note n="(l)" place="margin">Jude 12.</note> clouds carried hither and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114059:28"/>
thither by every wind: As <note n="(m)" place="margin">Socr. ſchol. hiſt. eccl. l. <hi>3</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eccebolius</hi> the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſt, who in <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time was a Chriſtian, in <hi>Julians</hi> a Pagan, after his death a Profeſſor of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity again; and hath this blurre left on him, That he was conſtant in his unconſtancie to his death. How many ſuch weather-cocks are there in the world who turn with every wind, conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves to the time, not truth: Well, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by worldly men charge Truth with fallibility and uncertainty. Or elſe they take notice of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregious Pride and Cenſoriouſneſſe, <note n="(n)" place="margin">Hermoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes erat natura turbulentus, &amp;c. Tertul. <hi>Jam. 3.17.</hi>
               </note> moroſity and ſelfiſhneſſe; ſtiling their own Conventicles the Elect of God, the Spouſe of Chriſt, the only pure and undefiled one, rejecting all others as polluted creatures, Reprobates, fuel for hell, and the like; as the <note n="(o)" place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. eccl. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Novatians</hi> of old,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> who ſtiled themſelves the Pure ones, and divers other Haereticks both in former and later times, I might inſtance in. This makes them tax Religion with pride &amp; unmanner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, with ſelf-ſeeking and uncharitableneſſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, Their diviſions and differences that were amongſt them; which made Pagans take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that <note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Amb. in</hi> 2 Tim. 2.20.</note> there were many Sects and Factions amongſt the Chriſtians; and hence conclude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Religion it ſelf, as a thing breeding and nouriſhing diviſions and diſtempers.</p>
            <p>But give me leave to tell you, their miſtake may be taken notice of to ariſe from theſe two things:</p>
            <p>Either, firſt, their not diſtinguiſhing between Truth and Haereſie, as if they were one and the ſame ſeed, producing the ſame fruit in all whom they poſſeſt. Thus they ſpeak evil of the things they <note n="(q)" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.12.</note> underſtand not, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:114059:29"/>Or ſecondly, Their not putting a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Orthodox and Heterodox profeſſors of Religion. Which error in the <note n="(r)" place="margin">Euſeb hiſt. eccl. l. <hi>4.</hi> c <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> Primitive time was no ſmal occaſion of ſlanders caſt upon the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and of ſad perſecutions raiſed againſt them. And hence it was that thoſe Primitive fathers were ſo much put upon it, to pen Pemonſtrances, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of faith, Apologies, and Confutations of Haeretical tenets; that they might vindicate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and cleer the Church of Chriſt from thoſe calumnies and falſe aſperſions that were occaſioned by their words and courſes, who were ſeduced by heterodox opinions.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> And is not here new cauſe of mourning, to hear Truth blaſphemed? This is that which ſads the ſpirits of good men; It is a day of trouble to them, becauſe a day of <note n="(s)" place="margin">Eſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 37 3.</note> blaſphemy; And that too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently procured by them who pretend to more light, piety and religion then others do. So that Chriſt may well take up thoſe words in the <note n="(t)" place="margin">Zach. 13.6.</note> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>I am wounded in the houſe of my friend;</hi> for ſuch they are in pretence, though in reality enemies. What pious ſpirit can chuſe but grieve to ſee the Daughter of heaven reproached; the Jewel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the Saints, abuſed; the generall and onely true Medicine of ſoules contemned; the Mirrour of Heaven ſpet upon; the Image of Gods mind moſt deſpitefully uſed: To hear Innocency charged with guilt; Simplicity, with deceit; Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, with falſhood; Antiquity, with novelty; Light called darkneſſe, Divine called humane, nay diabolical; Who can abſtain from tears? What have we (I beſeech you) to leave Poſterity, ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114059:29"/>
as this <hi>Way of Truth?</hi> If that be gone, the <note n="(u)" place="margin">1 Sam. 3.</note> glory is departed from Iſrael, and farewell all. Have we received it from our anceſtors in luſtre and purity, and is it not grievous to us, that in our time it ſhould be ſo mangled and defaced, that our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren after us (except it be timely prevented) will ſcarce be able to diſtinguiſh 'twixt it and Error? Why did the valiant Martyrs ſhed their precious blood, but to maintain this <hi>way of truth?</hi> &amp; ſhall we loſe and let it go at ſo cheap a rate, and not mourne for it? <note n="(w)" place="margin">Eſa. 36, 22, 37, 1.</note> The <hi>Jewes</hi> of old, when they heard blaſphemy, uſed to rend their cloaths, to teſtifie the inward rending of their hearts: Can ours be whole when the fooliſh people ſo much defame Gods truth, and blaſpheme his <note n="(x)" place="margin">Pſal. 74.18.</note> name?</p>
            <p>Well, this I am ſure of, That by this morris-dance of Haereticks, Gods truth is rendred in the opinion of carnal men, as a thing of ſo much uncertainty, vanity and deformity, that thoſe who otherwiſe would imbrace it, are kept back (like that <hi>Indian</hi> King from baptiſme, by beholding the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ungodly oppreſſing courſes); The weak are ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized and laid open to temptations, <note n="(y)" place="margin">Mat. 18.6. Mark 9.42. Luk. 17.2.</note> but woe to them that offend thoſe little ones that believe in Chriſt; it were better for them that a milſtone were hang'd about their necks, and they were caſt into the bottom of the ſea: The ſtrong, <note n="(z)" place="margin">2 Sam. 2.23.</note> like the army, ſtand at a gaze, as when <hi>Haſael</hi> lay dead be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and are retarded in ſtead of making pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gres to cleanſe theſe<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pauſan. l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Augean ſtables, &amp; purge out this leven, which elſe would leven the lump; their righteous ſoules are vexed, to ſee Religion made a coat for the Moon, or a Shipmans hoſe to ſerve all
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114059:30"/>
turns and purpoſes: The prophane are heartned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this way of truth, and their mouths wide-opened in ſcorns, ſcoms and reproches of it. Theſe things moved the bleſſed Apoſtle to that ſevere deſire, <note n="(b)" place="margin">Gal. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>I would,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>they were cut off that trouble you.</hi> And laſtly, God himſelf is provoked to wrath and indignation: For if <note n="(c)" place="margin">Cedr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. p. <hi>168.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperor was ſo much offended with the people of <hi>Antioch,</hi> for abuſing the Statue of his Empreſſe <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilla,</hi> that he devoted the place to ruine, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſlavery; what think you will become of thoſe that abuſe Religion, then which there is not a more excellent Image of Himſelfe in heaven or earth. And is not here cauſe to mourn?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Are not you a people whom God hath hedged in from the large Common of the world, for a part of his own Peculiar? You are famous in your pious Progenitors, who by their pleadings, writings, ſufferings, have ſtood like mighty bulwarks againſt Truths enemies. Are you not renowned in your Atchievements? glorious for Deliverances? envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Mercies? And what, ſhall all this ſet in a dark night of Error, and render you infamous to Poſterity? Shall famous <hi>England</hi> become an <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> of Mixtures, an Iſland of Monſters? Hath God done ſo much for you, and will you ſo ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite him, in expoſing his Truth to ſcorn? Do you not know the charge of Papiſts againſt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant truth, becauſe of Diviſions and Errors? we formerly have been able to retort this, by bidding them look at home; and muſt we now be ſilent?</p>
            <p>Beloved, were it ſome new, and not an ordinary tryal, that where <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Macar. hom. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> Truth is, the devil ſeeks to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:114059:30"/>
extinguiſh, or at leaſt ecclipſe its glory, by ſetting up Error to cloud it, or at leaſt to conflict with it and diſturb Truths quiet poſſeſſion: were this, I ſay, ſome ſtrange and uncouth thing, it were the more tolerable to be enſnared by it. But when 'tis a thing ſo ordinary, that leſſe or more, the Devils malice in every age of the Church hath been ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently diſcovered againſt the Truth; nay, God hath permitted ſuch blaſts and ſtorms to ariſe, for to put his people upon a ſtricter enquiry after truths confines; and that the light chaffe, and weighty wheat, the chaſte ſoule, and unchaſte fickle ſpirit, may be <note n="(e)" place="margin">Deut. 13.3.</note> diſtinguiſhed, diſcovered, and difference put between them. And now, when it is a thing ſo common; to be conquered by it, what will it argue at the beſt, but great inadvertencie and heedleſnes of ſpirit in you, and render you unexcuſable before Gods tribunal.</p>
            <p>Therefore I beſeech you, <note n="(f)" place="margin">Eph. 6.10.</note> be ſtrong in the Lord and in the power of his might; <note n="(g)" place="margin">1 Cor. 16.13.</note> Quit your ſelves like men; <note n="(h)" place="margin">Jude 3.</note> Contend earneſtly for the faith: alwayes remembring that ſpeech of <note n="(i)" place="margin">Fraus &amp; malitia haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum vel do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenda eſt tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vel cavenda eſt quam haeretica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum; vel irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imperitorum &amp; ſuperborum. <hi>Aug. cont. Adric.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> 
               <q>The fraud and malice of haereticks is either to be bewailed, becauſe they are men; or taken heed of and avoided, becauſe they are Haereticks; or to be laught at, becauſe they are either unskilfull and fooliſh, or elſe proud &amp; lofty; but alwayes to be ſhunned and avoided, as the means &amp; way of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ruine.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What (may ſome ſay) ſhould we do, that we may eſcape their Seducements?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. Get your minds furniſhed with ſaving, wholſome fundamental principles of Religion, out
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:114059:31"/>
of Truths record, the Word of God: for unbal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſed ſhips are ſoon oreſet, empty clouds whiſt to and fro by every blaſt; chaffe carried hither and thither with every breath of wind; and unfurniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unprincipled ſouls with heavenly truth, are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily like children for want of knowledge ſeduced and plunged in error: <note n="(k)" place="margin">Humana caecitas ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um non dirigit viam, niſi ipſe lucernam legis oſtendat, &amp;c. Cyp. ſer. <hi>5.</hi> de lapſ. <hi>Col. 3.16.</hi>
               </note> Therefore <hi>let the Word of Chriſt dwell plentifully in you in all knowledge and ſpirituall underſtanding.</hi> What is a Goldſmith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Touchſtone, or a Carpenter without his Rule? or a Chriſtian without the Word?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Reſt not in a bare literal knowledge, without the ſealing light of Gods ſpirit, affecting your ſouls with a proportionable love and liking to what is diſcovered in his Word unto you: for what we find not pleaſure, profit, or ſome reall worth and benefit in, we are eaſily inticed and prevailed with to let it go: but if once heavenly truths unload their treaſures of glory into our ſouls, ſo that we find and feel their vertue and influence in our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; beams of light enlightning, <note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal. 15.7.</note> delighting, and making glorious our minds; <note n="(m)" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.5.</note> Subduing power, throwing down Satans forts in our hearts; <note n="(n)" place="margin">2 Cor. 3. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> transforming grace, changing the whole man into the Lords image; Conſcience comforted, rectified, ſanctified; in a word, the ſoul <note n="(o)" place="margin">Eph. 3.19.</note> filled with Gods fulneſſe; It begets ſo great an aſſurance in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Religious verity, and ſo great an affection towards it becauſe of its goodneſſe, that Seducers loſe their labour and are fruitleſſe in their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to rob ſuch ſouls of Truth, becauſe they know its reall worth, and that there is nothing ſo good to them, in exchange for which they ſhould barter
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:114059:31"/>
and let it go. Only take care to grow and increaſe in this ſweet <note n="(p)" place="margin">Col. 1.2.2.</note> Experimentall knowledge, and moſt inward acquaintance with the way of truth, for<note n="(q)" place="margin">Nemo putet bonos poſſe de eccleſia diſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere: Triticum non rapit ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, nec arbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ſolida ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice fundatam procella ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit. Inanes pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leae tempeſtate jactantur, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validae arbores turbinis incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione evertun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Cyp. tract. 3. de ſimpl. praelat.</hi>
               </note> thereby you ſhall find your ſelves eſtabliſhed and ſtrongly rooted in the ſame, ſo that when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhall diſcover their levity, and in time of temptation ſhall fall away, you ſhall ſtand like mount Sion that cannot be moved.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note n="(r)" place="margin">Rom. 16.18. 2 Tim. 3.5.</note>
               <hi>Mark them that cauſe diviſions, and avoid them,</hi> ſaith St. Paul, <hi>for they ſerve not our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own bellies.</hi> Whether they ſeek to divide you from the Chriſtian verity by pernicious haereſies; or from the unity of Chriſts church and people, by peace diſturbing ſchiſmes and ſeperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Mark them with a note of infamy, as notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly <note n="(s)" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.3, 4.</note> proud, baſely ſelf-ſeeking, fooliſhly erring, Truths enemies, adverſaries to Peace, deſtroyers of Souls. And do not only mark, but alſo <note n="(t)" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.5.</note> avoid them after two or three admonitions: ſhun and avoid their diſcourſes and diſputes, which ſerve to no good purpoſe, but as foiles to their pride, riſes to their ſlanders, and (when they are more publike) as baits to deceive and delude poor ſouls; being like Fencers challenges, inventions to give the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter advantages to Cut-purſes to act their prizes. And as for their perſons, avoyd them too: O how zealouſly affected againſt Seducers were the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <note n="(u)" place="margin">2 Joh. 10, 11.</note> Chriſtians! <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt would not endure <note n="(w)" place="margin">Iraen. l <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> in the Bath at Epheſus with the haeretick <hi>Cerinthus;</hi> nor <hi>Polycarpus</hi> would entertain communion with <hi>Marcion,</hi> but defied him as the firſt begotten ſon of Satan. So zealous were the Apoſtles and their diſciples, ſaith <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> that they
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:114059:32"/>
would not communicate with haereticks in word, but were anſwerable to <note n="(x)" place="margin">Tit. 3.10, 11.</note> St. <hi>Pauls</hi> admonition, <hi>Eſchew him that is a Haeretick, after the firſt and ſecond admonition, knowing that ſuch a one is perverſe and ſinneth, being condemned of his own conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Forſake not your faithfull Paſtors, <note n="(y)" place="margin">Heb. 3.17.</note> but obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your ſouls. The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is well known, of the Wolves that offered to make a league with the Sheep, conditionally that they would put away their dogs; I need not make the application: but this I am ſure of, That the Devil, and Seducers who are his inſtruments, make it one of their firſt and chiefeſt deſignes, to alienate the hearts of people from their faithfull Guides; which if they can once effect, on the ruines of their reputation they uſe to lay the foundation of their own eſteem. Thus dealt the falſe Apoſtles with the Corinthians in the caſe of <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">2 Cor. 10.10.</note> His bodily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſay they is weak and contemptible; <note n="(a)" place="margin">2 Cor. 11.6, 11, 12, 13.</note> That he was rude in ſpeech; did not love and eſteem them as themſelves profeſt they did; and ſuch like ſtuffe to foment and increaſe jealouſies in their hearts, as do our Seducers now adayes, that they may make way for themſelves in the peoples eſtimation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Deſpiſe not the <note n="(b)" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.16.</note> Churches of Chriſt, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the Doctrine which they unanimouſly hold forth: For is not the <note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15.</note> Church the ground and <note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15.</note> pillar of truth, whereon God hangs forth to view that ſound direction to the world, which may guide their feet in the way of peace, to the reaching of everlaſting bliſſe?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Forſake not the <note n="(d)" place="margin">Heb. 10.25</note> aſſembling of your ſelves
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:114059:32"/>
together; be not a ſtranger to the publike Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, as the cuſtome of ſome is, who think Chriſt is not to be found except in a wilderneſſe or in a chamber: <note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 24, 26.</note> but <hi>go not after them,</hi> ſays he.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Endeavour after a greater meaſure of morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of corrupt paſſions and affections, which <note n="(a)" place="margin">Si vis lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine claro cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere verum, gaudia pelle, pelle timorem, spent<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſugato, nec dolor adſit: nubila mens eſt vincta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fraenis haec ubi regna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Boet. l. <hi>1.</hi> de conſol. philoſ. metro <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> ſo cloud the mind, that Truth cannot in its luſtre appear unto it; and makes the heart, like thoſe that are <note n="(b)" place="margin">Ecclus. c 27.</note> Lunaticks, full of changes from <note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.13</note> bad to worſer, but never right; never ſetled, but full of motion, <note n="(d)" place="margin">Camerar. Hor. Succiſ. par. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> like a horſe ſtung with waſps that runs, capers and curvets, to little purpoſe. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt paſſions and affections prevailing, the ſoul is like to an <note n="(e)" place="margin">Prov. 25.28.</note> unfenced city, open to rapine and ruine by every enemy. They are, in a word, ſuch a complying party with whatever is evil, that if Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers can but find a way to parley with them, and proffer them what is proportionable to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; if they have but the art to ſute their bait to thoſe <note n="(f)" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.18, 19. Jude 16, 17, &amp;c</note> luſts or paſſions that have domination and rule within, be it <note n="(g)" place="margin">3 Joh. 9.</note> ambition, <note n="(h)" place="margin">Tit. 1.11.</note> covetouſnes, feare, or whatever it be; That ſoul is eaſily made a prey of by theſe Haereticks. Therefore, if ever you would be ſafe, be not content without the death of theſe.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Grow in grace, <note n="(i)" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.5, 6, 7, 8, 11.</note> Adde vertue to vertue, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> preſſes, that an abundant entrance may be adminiſtred to you into the everlaſting kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. If you would not be led away with the error of the wicked (ſaith the ſame Apoſtle) <note n="(k)" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.17 18.</note> grow in grace, for 'tis that is only able to <note n="(l)" place="margin">Heb. 13.9.</note> eſtabliſh the heart againſt temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and ſeducements. <note n="(m)" place="margin">1 Cor. 14, 20.</note> A ſilly child is eaſily
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:114059:33"/>
cozened with copper inſtead of gold; but as <note n="(n)" place="margin">Heb. 5.14.</note> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and diſcerning increaſes in him, he is free from that deluſion. A <note n="(o)" place="margin">Eph. 4.14.</note> weak body reels to and fro, and every blaſt of wind is ready to throw him down, but as ſtrength grows he becomes more able daily to endure its ſtrongeſt blaſts: ſo is it with the ſoule, according to the meaſure of grace it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with, 'tis able to reſiſt and ſtand out againſt ſeducements.</p>
            <p>Above all, endeavour to increaſe Humility, which is the <note n="(p)" place="margin">Jam. 4.6.</note> womb of vertue; <note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Pet. 5 5.</note> a ſweet adornment and an excellent fence againſt this monſter Haereſie: which had ſome cheriſht, the Church had not been peſtered with this evil, nor had this plague of Error found ſuch footing in this our Iſrael.</p>
            <p>If any ſpark of this helliſh fire at any time light on your ſouls, dally not with it, but be ſure to call in help betimes to quench it: there's many a houſe hath been conſumed to aſhes, by the inhabitants <note n="(r)" place="margin">Et neglecta ſolent incendia ſumere viris. <hi>Horat. 1. ep. 19.</hi> Facilius eſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludere pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſa quàm rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp; non ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere quàm admiſſa mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari. <hi>Sea. l. 1. de ira, c. 7.</hi>
               </note> inadvertencie, not heeding the firſt kindling of this miſchief in their ſouls; and others by an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weening opinion of their own ability to extinguiſh it at pleaſure; and perhaps ſome few out of an over-tenderneſſe of their own repute, as being loth that others ſhould take notice what fooliſh, dark, heterodox reaſonings they have had within, (for as ſuch, at their firſt encounter, there are many have lookt upon them, though afterward they have changed their opinion.) Whatever the pretence and colour be, deal in this buſineſſe as you uſually do in your own dwellings: If you ſpy within your doors a ſtrange face walking up and down at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, you fall to queſtioning what he is, whence he
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:114059:33"/>
comes, what he would have? Which not being able to ſatisfie you in, if you be not able your ſelf, help is called in, <note n="(s)" place="margin">Scintillae ſtatim ut apparet extinguenda eſt &amp; fermentum à maſſae vicinio removendum, ſecandae putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae carnes, &amp; ſcabioſum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal à caulis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium repellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum; ne tota domus, maſſa, corpus, &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cora, ardeat, corrumpatur, putreſcat, intereant, &amp;c. <hi>Hier. in Gal. 5.</hi>
               </note> and you thruſt him out of doors; Or if you find his intention be theft, or murder, he is delivered up to the Magiſtrate to receive condign puniſhment to his demerit. So I beſeech you, if ſtrange Opinions look into your ſoules, and in your thoughts walk up and down, let them be <note n="(t)" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.21. Iſa. 8.20.</note> exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and brought to the teſt of Law and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony; thereby you will find they are miſchievous both in their nature, and in their intent and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, they come not but to devoure; therefore harbour them not in your ſpirits, but call in aid from your faithfull Shepherds, and able Chriſtians; alſo cry for help from Heaven to deliver you from them, to deſtroy and root them out, that they may no more take place in mens hearts to their ruine and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, worthy Senators, give me leave in all humility to make my addreſſe to you in the behalf of Truth. Are not you Truths guardians, foſter-fathers to whoſe protection God hath committed Truth? Doth he not ſtile you <note n="(u)" place="margin">Pſal. 47.9.</note> Shields, in his Word? and I hope He ſhall never have cauſe to complain of you, as that Warriour did of his, <note n="(w)" place="margin">Clypeus meus me ſefellie <hi>Cauſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>My ſhield hath deceived me.</hi> Oh what ſhall we do, if Truth be blaſted and blaſphemed! if that once faile! <note n="(x)" place="margin">Prov. 29.18.</note> Where there is no viſion, the people periſh. And can you be ſafe? will the God of truth protect you? No; from the <note n="(y)" place="margin">Ezek. 9.3, 5. Rev. 8.5.</note> Altar comes revenging fire. Or will thoſe that deſtroy Truth, ſpare you? Certainly no; <note n="(z)" place="margin">Haeretici, quos non poſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſermone decipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, eos putant gladie eſſe feri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endos. <hi>Hier. in orat. in Auxen. de non trad. Baſil.</hi>
               </note> There are none ſo keen as theſe, to ruine whatever oppoſes them. I
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:114059:34"/>
beſeech you, without offence give me leave to tell you, We have juſt cauſe to feare, if Truth be not ſupported and inthroniz'd, having enjoyed ſo cleer and long diſcoveries thereof as we have done; that God will ſend a darker Night on this poor Iſland, then ever was the <hi>Marian</hi> Perſecution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> But perhaps you may ask me, what is the way whereby Error may be ſuppreſt, and Truth eſtabliſhed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. Command and haſten, I beſeech you, the buſines of Catechiſing, whereby poor ſoules may be taught the principles of Religion in the plaineſt way and manner, that there may be milk for babes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Plant a good peece of Battery in every emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent place, eſpecially there where Errors already begin to thrive and proſper: I mean ſuch Miniſtry, as may be able to manifeſt the folly, falſhood, and danger of ſuch Errors as do ariſe, and diſcover the madneſſe of Seducers, that their <note n="(a)" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.9.</note> fooliſhneſſe may appeare to all, and their <note n="(b)" place="margin">Tit. 1.11.</note> mouths be ſtopt, or at leaſt their danger prevented, that they deſtroy not the precious ſoules of people. And here give me leave to ſuggeſt unto you, That there are many learned men in this Kingdome, whom God hath not gifted with Elocution and other the like abilities for Pulpit-work, yet would be very fit to maintain the Truth by their Pen, againſt deſtroying Errors, might they but have encouragement, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient maintenance be inabled thereunto.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Settle with all convenient ſpeed your <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith,</hi> wherein people may take notice what is allowed for Truth, upon mature debate: whereby you ſhall not only ſettle that good opinion
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:114059:34"/>
the Churches of Chriſt have alway had ſince the Reformation, of this poor Iſland; but alſo put ſuch a help into the hands of people, that they ſhall with little paines diſcern what's right or wrong; And as a common Standard being ſet up, and ſtrengthened by your Sanction, there's hope our Differences may vaniſh.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Permit not <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov. 22.28</hi> Blandimenta vagae fugies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitdtis. <hi>Grat.</hi>
               </note> old Landmarks to be removed without abſolute neceſſity: for, beſides the muſe it breeds in peoples mindse, and great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage it gives to incredulity in point of Truth, there is alſo another evil in it, which is, That changes are very dangerous in point of <note n="(d)" place="margin">Eventus varios res nova ſemper habet.</note> event and iſſue.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Suffer not Fundamental truths, as, Chriſts deity, The reality of his incarnation, paſſion, or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, The bleſſed Trinity, Scriptures autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, verity, and the like; to be queſtioned by every jugling Sophiſter, or vagrant itinerant Huckſter, nor toſt on the tongue of every profane debauched perſon, nor much leſſe to be libel'd and pamphleted againſt by every unſavoury, ignorant, blaſphemous wretch. All theſe kindes of people are like the <note n="(e)" place="margin">Cauſin. l. <hi>12</hi> c. <hi>58.</hi>
               </note> glaſſe that was in the temple of <hi>Smirna,</hi> which preſented thoſe things that were exceeding lovely in themſelves, in moſt horrid miſhapen forms: therefore they are fitter to be broken in ſhivers then maintained and countenanced.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Take heed how you tolerate Schiſme; for in a little time, without great care, it will open the door to Haereſie; as little theeves creeping in at the window, unlock the gate for greater to enter in. And be confident, that looſe Government is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the mother of looſe Tenets in higher mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:114059:35"/>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Gaudet ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus orbis de u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate catholica praeter partem Affricae, in qua incendium de ſcintilla con <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, (de Donato loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur) <hi>Op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at. Mile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Donatus</hi> was firſt a Schiſmatick, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſomewhat worſe: He that expects to find a Church in this world void of blemiſh, had beſt (as <note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. eccl. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Conſtantine</hi> tels <hi>Aceſius</hi> the Novatian Biſhop) get a ladder and climbe alone into heaven.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Take ſpeciall care of our fountains, the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities; that Learning may be encouraged, and Doctrines contrary to ſoundneſſe of faith, or holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life and manners, be wholly there ſuppreſt. For want of this, becauſe there have been Errors in the firſt concoction, they could never in many be mended to this preſent day; but many Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have been poiſoned with Arminianiſme, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinianiſme, yea downright Popery: it was the milk they ſuckt at the Univerſity from ill Tutors, and their people muſt either take that or none, for they have no better to give them. It were not a little to be wiſht, that what <note n="(h)" place="margin">Euſeb hiſt. eccl. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> writes concerning the Primitive Chriſtians in <hi>Egypt,</hi> were practiſed there; I mean, that reading the Scriptures, and pious exerciſes, might be more in uſe amongſt them. <note n="(i)" place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. eccl. l <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi> Nullis tutius infirma at as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittitur, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his qui &amp; piè docti, &amp; doctè piiſunt. <hi>Hyper. opuſc. c. 4.</hi>
               </note> What a flouriſhing School was <hi>Alexandria,</hi> by reaſon of <hi>Clement, Ammonius, Panthenus, Origen, Heracles, Didymus,</hi> and divers others; who being men of extraordinary piety and learning, were Inſtruments to breed not a few, that were famous men for Learning and Religion in the Church of God.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Suffer not the Church, for relation or by-reſpects, to be peſtered with unſound or illiterate perſons, who have not the <note n="(k)" place="margin">Iſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 4.</note> tongue of the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are not well <note n="(l)" place="margin">Mat. 13 52.</note> taught to the Kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <note n="(m)" place="margin">Mich. 3.8.</note> want judgement, <note n="(n)" place="margin">2 Tim 2.15</note> and are not able to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:114059:35"/>
divide the Word of God aright, <note n="(o)" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.16 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2 Tim. 3.13.</note> Take no heed to their doctrine, but are deceivers, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <note n="(p)" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.14 1 Tim 5.17, 18</note> Take heed of ſcandalous Maintenance, 'tis the way to breed a baſe &amp; ſcandalous Miniſtry in time; like <note n="(q)" place="margin">1 King. 12.31.</note> 
               <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Prieſts, or <note n="(r)" place="margin">Judg. 17.5, 10.</note> 
               <hi>Micha's</hi> ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ekels Levite.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Encourage Orthodoxneſſe, but diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance Erroneous perſons &amp; opinions: And that not only in verbal, but alſo in real encouragements, as, by your Proviſion and Maintenance.<note n="(s)" place="margin">Theodore. l. 1. c. 11.</note> 
               <hi>(y)</hi> So <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> did, and divers pious Emperors, who che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed Truths champions, but diſcouraged Errors huckſters. By your Lawes and Ordinances, ſtop Seducers mouths, but command that Truth be taught: 'Tis a Princely work to make it your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, that people may know the ſacred truth of God. By your Cenſures and Puniſhments, let all the World take notice you are ſenſible of Gods diſhonour, and that there is nothing more you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, then to do him ſervice in this great buſineſſe: If nothing elſe will do it, <note n="(t)" place="margin">Deut. 13.5.10.</note> the Seducing Prophet muſt die the death, for offering to thruſt Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from him; <hi>Eliah</hi> ſlayes <note n="(u)" place="margin">1 King. 18.40.</note> Baals prophets, the like doth <note n="(w)" place="margin">2 King. 10.24.</note> 
               <hi>Jehu,</hi> 
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">2 King. 11.18.</note> The people of the land ſlay <hi>Mattan.</hi> If any offer ſacrifice to Idols on altars, let him be <note n="(y)" place="margin">Gladio ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore ſterneretur.</note> cut off with the ſword, ſayes <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine; Valentinian, Theodoſius, Martian,</hi> were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like diſpoſed againſt ſuch perſons. I confeſſe, ſuch executions ſhould be after other means made uſe of, all endeavour fruſtrated; deſperate Doctrines broached, with Haereſie, Blaſphemy, or Sedition mingled. <note n="(z)" place="margin">Fulmina paucorum peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo cadunt, omnium metu.</note> The thunderbolt ſmites few, but frights many.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:114059:36"/>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But ſome may object and ſay, What would you have us do, there are many of them are holy and pious men?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> You hear what the Apoſtle ſays, that many may have <note n="(a)" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.5.</note> a forme, and yet deny the power of godlineſſe. The wolf in the fable, that he might not be ſuſpected, but the more eaſily make his prey of the ſilly ſheep, put on a skin of theirs: The ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd diſcovers the guile, and hangs him up in his diſguiſe; his fellow-ſhepherds blame him for hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſilly ſheep; To cleer himſelf from cruelty, he wiſhes them to open his skin, which having done they eaſily diſcover that he was not miſtaken as they conceived. I need not trouble you with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king application, 'tis obvious to your view.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Why ſhould you think, to ſay, He is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt or a pious man, ſhould be a fooliſh plea in caſe of abuſing Coyne, Theft, Treaſon, or the like; and yet ſhould be of weight and force in this farre greater buſineſſe, and more horrid miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe?</p>
            <p>Well, I ſhall ſay no more: but to conclude; Bleſſed be God who hath put it into your hearts to humble your ſoules this day before him, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Nation ſo to do: In the ſence of that Oath of God that lies upon you, to extirpate Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Superſtition, Haereſie, Schiſme, Profaneſſe, and whatſoever is contrary to found doctrine, and the power of godlineſſe: In the apprehenſion of Gods protection of You, but miſery that lies on the Land, by abominable Blaſphemies and damnable Haereſies, tending to the ſubverſion of the Faith; whereby reproach and contempt hath been caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:114059:36"/>
Gods name, and ſaving truths, the immortall ſoules of people in danger of ſwift deſtruction, and the Kingdome brought into a perilous condition. Bleſſed be the God of heaven who hath cauſed you to take notice, <hi>That not to uſe your power to ſuppreſſe this miſchief, is to make your ſelves partakers of theſe mens ſinnes and puniſhments.</hi> And now (worthy Senators) what remaines, but that according to your profeſſion you imploy and improve the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of your power, That nothing be ſaid or done againſt, but for the Truth.</p>
            <p>I beſeech the Rock of Eternity to act and enable you by his grace, to put under his everlaſting arms and beare you up in the putting into Execution this your Ordinance and reſolution; Make you like thoſe <note n="(b)" place="margin">Rev. 4.6.8.</note> glorious creatures full of eyes, that you may ſet about this buſineſſe; <note n="(c)" place="margin">Hoc pietatis genus eſt, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercere infantia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> criminis, ne ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veneſcat aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis. Caſſiod. l. <hi>5.</hi> ep. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> Timouſly, before it be too late; Conſcientiouſly, as a duty; Affectionately, as a thing of glory to God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to your ſelves and this poor Kingdome; Unanimouſly, as a way of ſtrength; Fully, with due reſpect to every Truth, without reſpect to any Perſon; Couragiouſly, not fearing oppoſition. Conſider, you have a good God to ſupport you; 'Tis the way to have a good Conſcience in the ſenſe of duty to cheer you; Good men will bleſſe God for you; And if you ſtrive <note n="(d)" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> lawfully, you may expect confidently that Heaven will crown you.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Vid. Cauſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>71.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> tels us a ſtory, That amongſt the <hi>Magi</hi> in <hi>Perſia,</hi> there were three hills; when people came to the firſt, they heard a claſhing of arms; when they came to the ſecond, they heard a confuſed noiſe; but when they reached the third,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:114059:37"/>
they heard nothing but ſongs of triumph. The ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible noiſe of Arms you have heard already; God grant, if it be his will, our cares in this poor Iſland may never more be acquainted with thoſe dreadfull ſounds: You are now come to the ſecond hill, the confuſed noiſe of Error, the language of Babel: Be now but valiant, go on with reſolution, and I doubt not but ere long you ſhall hear the voice of Victorious ſongs of triumph, Halelujahs to our GOD.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
